<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The art of thriving. Or, The plaine path-way to preferment. Together with The mysterie and misery of lending and borrowing. As also a table of the expence of time and money. Published for the common good of all sorts, &amp;c.</title>
            <title>Tom of all trades</title>
            <author>Powell, Thomas, 1572?-1635?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 137 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09899</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114990</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850210</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850210</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15397</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09899)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15397)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 970:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The art of thriving. Or, The plaine path-way to preferment. Together with The mysterie and misery of lending and borrowing. As also a table of the expence of time and money. Published for the common good of all sorts, &amp;c.</title>
                  <title>Tom of all trades</title>
                  <author>Powell, Thomas, 1572?-1635?</author>
                  <author>Powell, Thomas, 1572?-1635? Wheresoever you see mee, trust unto your selfe. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 254, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] H[arper] for Benjamin Fisher, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Talbot in Aldersgate street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635 [i.e. 1636]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: T.P., i.e. Thomas Powell.</note>
                  <note>The first part originally published in 1631 as: Tom of all trades.</note>
                  <note>"The mistery and misery of lending and borrowing. By Tho: Powel, Gent.", a reprint of his "Wheresoever you see mee, trust unto your selfe", has separate title page with imprint "London: printed by Thomas Harper for Benjamin Fisher .. 1636"; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Success --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Loans --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15397:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15397:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The art of Thriving.</hi> OR, The plaine path-way to PREFERMENT. Together with The Myſterie and Miſery of <hi>Lending</hi> and <hi>Borrowing.</hi> As alſo a Table of the expence of Time and Money.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Conſider it ſeriouſly.</item>
               <item>Examine it judiciouſly.</item>
               <item>Remember it punctually.</item>
               <item>And thrive accordingly.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Publiſhed for the common good of all ſorts, &amp;c. by T. Powel.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. H.</hi> for <hi>Benjamin Fiſher,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Talbot in Alderſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate ſtreet. 1635.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15397:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15397:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a method in all arts, and a myſtery, but in none more then in the <hi>art of thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,</hi> being the very Center to which all the other arts doe tend, and for which they were invented. <hi>Magiſter artis venter,</hi> and what is that but Thriving? Now in the ſtudy of this great art, you muſt make the world your Liberary, and learne to reade men as well as bookes: and yet not to diſcourage you in the whole volume of this
<pb facs="tcp:15397:3"/>ſcience, you are to turne over but three leaves, onely ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what cloſe writ, very hard to reade, and when you are once out, can hardly begin againe: Times, Trades, and Debts, this is that ſcrew of a three fold twinding; for if you ſcrew not your fortunes the right way, as it is in all ſcrewes, you may turne and work your heart out, remember but that firſt: And let me tell you, Time is the hinge of all thriving, Trades are the doores on which good hopes may turn, and ſtand long enough; if Debts thoſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining leavers of husbandry, fling not all off the hooks. Thus then thinke with your ſelfe, to Time a buſineſſe well, and to
<pb facs="tcp:15397:3"/>begin buſineſſe in time, is the very key to the door of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and thinke the loſſe of a minute more dear than the loſſe of a pound; for certainly of all expences, the expence of Time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the coſtlieſt: which, mindefull reader, that thou mayſt know now, learn to prize and reckon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hy time right: for as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>Lucilius, quem mihi dabis qui aliquod pretium tempori ponat? qui diem eſtimet? qui intelligat ſe quotidie mori:</hi> and therfore that made him ſay in the beginning of the ſame Epiſtle to <hi>Lucilius, vindica te tibi,</hi> as if a man were to be revenged upon himſelfe for haſting his owne death by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſſe of Time. Now therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat thou maiſt know how to
<pb facs="tcp:15397:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>take and redeeme thy Time. I have here ſet before thee, a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of each minute of thy life, this is the firſt leafe, and now I paſſe to the next, having not time to ſpeake of Time.</p>
            <p n="2">2 All men are or would be rich; even the ſluggard wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, though he hath not: 'Tis eaſie indeed to covet the top of wit or preferment, but to get up the hill, <hi>hic labor, hoc opus;</hi> there is a buſineſſe indeed! the wayes to thrive are manifold, yet one good is worth all, and in effect is all: onely all the Art is finding and catching it: Could <hi>Archimedes</hi> but have found foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for his Mathematicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, he would have done wonders.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15397:4"/>
            <q>
               <l>Give me but footing where my ſelfe may ſtand,</l>
               <l>From their fixt Baſe I'le hoyſt both ſea and land.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Boldly ſpoke, and bravely meant; and queſtionleſſe, if you could have done the one for him, he would have perform'd the other for you: Thinke not, thriftie would be, that I by his example enjoyn the impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, or to build caſtles in the ayre, but meerely to ſhew thee how out of nothing to produce ſomething, and thus I apply it. Could a young man once take hold or ſetling in preferment, where he may but fixe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of his hopes, then may he eaſily drive the world before
<pb facs="tcp:15397:5"/>him, and ſo mount up to wealth. Now who is able to le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell to a beginner the ſhorteſt cut, or ſcore him the very way to thrive, if he either ſtand in his owne light through wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or cut the throat as it were of all his hopes, through de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of better; the foole thus concluding with himſelfe, <hi>He that's borne under a three-penny Planet, ſhall never be worth a groat.</hi> To him, and to him I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate not. What ſhould I talke to ſuch of Promotion? But to a forward ſpirit, and a manly heart, prepared for induſtry, and reſolved to ſtand to his curſe in Paradice, I commend this my Grammar of Trades. Nor thinke hopefull Reader I
<pb facs="tcp:15397:5"/>have prefixt a ſpecious title to make the ſale more oylie, I would I were dead if I care whether you buy or burne it, onely I would have thee reade and be wiſe, labour and be rich.</p>
            <p>The old Paradox is witry and true. <hi>Quiſque ſuae fortunae, faber.</hi> Every man ſits at the very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile and forge of his own For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune-making: now then if you can ſee to ſtrike the Iron, while it is hot, that is, while time and the hand of Providence hold forth the opportunity, you may make your trade, but if you lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger till it be cold, it will coſt you another Heate. <hi>Experto mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi credite.</hi> Now therefore that no man may over-ſlip his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, or be puſled for want of
<pb facs="tcp:15397:6"/>light, to ſee when it is offered, or to conduct him forward, when it is found, Loe here a Torch held out before him, pointing the plaine high way to preferment, in all Profeſſions, Trades, and Arts, found out by an old traveller in the Sea of Experience, <hi>Longis erroribus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, qui mores Hominum, &amp;c.</hi> who now ſtands after all his folly, and ruines, a Land-marke, to the generall good of others.</p>
            <p>To the Father and his ſonnes, to the Mother and every Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers childe, to the Scholler, the Apprentice, the Navigator, the Husbandman, the Courtier, and the Souldier, whether in hopes or in deſpaire, ſtanding, riſing, or falling, I bequeath
<pb facs="tcp:15397:6"/>this my Legacy, my Looking-glaſſe to promotion, my Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar of Trades.</p>
            <p n="3">3 And ſince in the voyage to Promotion, Lending is the Rocke, and Borrowing is the Gulfe, I have diſcovered them both in the end, leſt your ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der endeavours ſhould tare againſt the one, or be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in the other. Farewell, and where you ſee me, if you meane to Thrive, looke to your ſelfe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine living and dead, T. Powel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:15397:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15397:7"/>
            <head>The art of Thriving. <hi>The Contents.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1 AN Introduction to the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing diſcourſe with the occaſion.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1</hi> Direction for a Scholler in his Education, Maintenance, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement in his minority.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2</hi> In the Vniverſity.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3</hi> In the Miniſtry.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4</hi> In Benefices abroad.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2 Promotions following by Law.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1</hi> Civill.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2</hi> Common.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:15397:8"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>3 For the Phyſitian, and his meanes of Advancement.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4 The Apprentice with the due Election of Trades, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of Merchandize.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5 The Navigator his way of Advancement &amp; imployment.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6 The Husbandman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7 The Courtier.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8 The Souldier.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1</hi> By Sea.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2</hi> By Land.</item>
                  </list>
                  <hi>Directions for matching of daughters.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:15397:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <list>
               <head>The Myſtery, &amp;c. <hi>Contents.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> The ſcope of the following Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, firſt of the Borrower, ſecondly of the Lender.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1</hi> The Courtiers Method.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2</hi> The Innes of Court man.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3</hi> The Country Gentleman.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> Their ſeverall cauſes of Inſolency.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> The ſundry wayes and weapons wherewith they fence with their Creditors.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1</hi> The Innes of Court mans.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2</hi> The Country Gentleman.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3</hi> The City borrower.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:15397:9"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4</hi> Their noted places of refuge.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5</hi> Their dayes of Iubile and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> The markes of a Conſcious deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, with the diſcipline of the Mace.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> The Lenders or Creditors part.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1</hi> The charitable extent of the Creditors curteſie.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2</hi> The reaſons thereof.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3</hi> The myſtery of Multiplication.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7 1</hi> Certaine ſignes fore-running and fore-ſhewing the <hi>Wonderfull Cracke.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2</hi> The Recovery.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3</hi> A voyage to two new Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15397:9"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The art of Thriving:</hi> OR, The plaine Path-way to <hi>Preferment.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>RINITY Terme was now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; For by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the time it could be no other parcell of the yeere. In that the Scrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners at <hi>Temple-barrr,</hi> had no imployment, but writing of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15397:10"/>blanke Bonds, and texting of Bills, for letting of Chambers in <hi>Chancery</hi>-lane. The Vintners of <hi>Fleet-ſtreet</hi> diſcharged their Iourney-men; A generall hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility more than uſuall poſſeſt the Cookery of <hi>Ram Alley.</hi> The Oſtlers of <hi>Holborne</hi> had more than ordinary care to lay up their Gueſts bootes, rather for feare of their ſlipping out of Towne, than for any good ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance towards them. And your Country Attorneyes would no longer by any means endure the unwholſome ayre of an Eight-penny Ordinary. Every one that had wherewith to diſcharge his Horſe out of the ſtable, ſtrove who ſhould
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15397:10"/>firſt be gone. And amongſt the reſt, my ſelfe made ſhift for ſo much money as wherewith to abate the fury of Miſtriſſe <hi>Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> mine hoſteſſe, and ſo I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted likewiſe.</p>
                  <p>At the top of <hi>Highgate</hi> hill I overtooke a Gentleman of <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> riding home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, whom I well knew; Him I ſaluted cheerefully, and he received me lovingly. But in travelling together (Mee thought) he was not Maſter of that mirthful diſpoſition which he was wont to carry along with him to ſhorten the way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt his houſe and <hi>London,</hi> I gave him to underſtand, how ſtrange, and notable this altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15397:11"/>appeared in him; And withall deſired to know ſo much of the occaſion thereof as might bee impartible to a friend of ſo ſmall growth. To which he anſwered thus; Sir, I come from <hi>London,</hi> (it is true) from the Terme (It is certaine true) from <hi>London</hi> and Terme, True and certaine in nothing but expences in all things, yet I would have you know, that it is neither the Thunderclap of diſſolving an <hi>Iniunction,</hi> nor the Doomeſday of a <hi>Decree,</hi> nor Councellers <hi>Fees,</hi> nor Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies <hi>Bills</hi> in a language able to fright a man out of his wits, can proſcribe me my wonted mirth. It is ſomething nearer and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15397:11"/>(my deare friend) that robs me of that cheere which uſed to lift me up into the very Spheare, where <hi>Iove</hi> himſelfe ſits to bid al his gueſts welcome right heartily.</p>
                  <p>I remember me of Children, ſixe Sonnes, and three Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, of whom I am the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Father. In that, beſides the ſcars which my unthriftineſſe hath dinted upon their fortunes the wounds of unequall times, and a tempeſtuous age ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching are like to take away from them all hope of out-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the low water ebbe of the evill day all meanes of thriving by honeſt paynes, ſtudy or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry are bereft them. The
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15397:12"/>Common upon which induſtry ſhould depaſture is overlaid, Numerouſneſſe ſpoiles all, and poverty ſels all at an under va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue.</p>
                  <p>In this caſe (Sir) what can be adviſed? Whereunto I thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed.</p>
                  <p>Sir, I have heedfully atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you in the delivery of your perplexed thoughts, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the care which you have of your children, taking the true, and even levell of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clention of arts, the diſtent of trades, and trading, the poverty of all profeſſions, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, not of ours onely, but of all Chriſtian clymates at this preſent, tending rather to a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15397:12"/>more contagion in the generall ayre, then a calmer tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (for ought that yet appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth) as for the ſtormineſſe of the ſea of ſtate forraigne or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticke, let us leave the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and leſſer veſſels that be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to it, unto the proper Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, Maſters, and Marriners, who have the charge to attend the line, or plye at the tackle, we are but poore paſſengers, and may aſſure our ſelves to partake in their boone voyage, if they ſucceed well, as they may be certaine to ſuffer in the ſame Shipwracke with us, if we miſcarry. I addreſſe me to give you the beſt adviſe I can touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the preferment of your ſixe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15397:13"/>ſonnes and three daughters, in manner following.</p>
                  <p>It is true in moſt Gentlemen, and very likely in you, as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, living onely upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue of lands. That the height of their Husbandry amounts to no more than to cleere the laſt halfe yeeres booking, and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing at the rent day. That their credit may hold up and keepe reputation till the next enſuing that againe.</p>
                  <p>When you dye, the eldeſt Son claimes the inheritance of what you leave, thanke God, and nature for it, your ſelfe leaſt of all, and your fatherly providence never a whit.</p>
                  <p>If you take ſome courſe in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15397:13"/>your life time to make the reſt of your Children ſome ſmall portions or eſtates out of the whole of your lands. It is tenne to one but you deſtroy both him, and them by that meanes.</p>
                  <p>For the heire commonly ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to uphold the reputation of his Anceſtors, He abates no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his fathers accuſtomed expences towards the raiſing of thoſe portions or eſtates ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted. And they on the other ſide, preſume ſo much upon the hope thereof, that no profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will fit them. To be a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> (with them) is to be but a <hi>Pedant.</hi> A <hi>Lawyer,</hi> a <hi>mercenarie</hi> fellow. A Shop-keeper, a man moſt ſubject to the moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15397:14"/>Cracke, and a creature whoſe welfare depends much upon his Wives well bearing, and faire carrriage. What is then to be done?</p>
                  <p>Surely it would be wiſhed, ſeeing God and nature hath provided for the eldeſt, your younger ſonnes, and your daughters; eſpecially, being worſt able to ſhift, ſhould be by you provided for in the firſt place, while your Land is of virgin reputation, while it is chaſt, and undiſhoneſted by committing of ſingle fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Country Creditors, that trade without ſheets (that is) by <hi>Pole deed,</hi> onely for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of coſts; or at leaſt, before
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15397:14"/>it have defiled the bed of its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation by proſtituting to the adulterous imbracings of a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Scrivener: But eſpecially, before it grow ſo impudent, as to lye downe in the Market place, and to ſuffer every petty Clarke to bring its good name upon Record, and charge it that it was taken in the very fact be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene other mens ſheets. As in this Statute, or in that Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Take heed of that by any meanes. And be ſure to match your eldeſt ſonne, when your credit is cryed up to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, while your heire is yet in your power to diſpoſe, and will bend to your will, before his bloud begin to feele the heate
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15397:15"/>of any affections kindling about him, or before he can tell what difference is betwixt a blacke wrought Waſtcoate, with a white apron and a looſe bodied gowne without an apron. Put him off in his beſt clothes (I meane) in the aſſurance of your lands, ſell him at the higheſt rate. Then dicotomize the whole portion of his wife into ſeverall ſhares betwixt your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther children. Not ſhare and ſhare like, but to every each one the more according to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: Let impotencie, decrept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ill favourdneſſe and inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie, rob the other of ſo much money as they have done them of comelineſſe, acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15397:15"/>beauty, and wit.</p>
                  <p>Put them not into any courſe of living according to any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript order, or method of your owne election. But according to their inclination and additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeeing that every one by inſtinct of nature, delighteth in that wherein he is like to be moſt excellent. And delight, and pride in any thing underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, makes all obſtacles in the way of attaining to perfection of no difficulty.</p>
                  <p>Now in the next place take heed that you put off thoſe your ſonnes whom you finde fit and addicted to be bred in the <hi>Miniſterie,</hi> or made up to the law, or to be apprentized
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15397:16"/>betimes, and before they take the taynt of too much liberty at home.</p>
                  <p>And when they be put forth, call them not home ſpeedily to reviſit their fathers houſe, no not ſo much as Hoſpitably by any meanes.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:15397:16"/>
                     <head>In the firſt place take your direction for the SCHOLLER.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>His Education.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>His Maintenance.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>His Advancement.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>FOr his Education. The Free-Schooles generally afford the beſt breeding in good let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
                     <p>So many of them alſo afford ſome reaſonable means in ayde of young Schollers, for their diet, lodging, and teaching, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them by the Founders or Benefactors of ſuch Schools.</p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15397:17"/>
                     <p>Some of them be of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of ſome Kings and Queenes of this Land, and they are commonly in the gift of the King, or his Provoſt, or Subſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute in that behalfe. Others be of the foundation of ſome Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies or Societies incorporate. And they are commonly in the gift of ſuch Maſters, Wardens, Preſidents, and their Senior fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, ſuch chiefe officers of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other title, or ſuch Maſter Wardens, and Aſſiſtants, or ſuch Oppoſers, Viſitants, or Committees of ſuch bodies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively as be appointed thereunto. Others be of the foundation of ſome private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: And they are for the moſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15397:17"/>part in the gift of the Executor, Heire, or Feoffees of ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, according to the purport of his Will, or Grant, or both.</p>
                     <p>Of every of which ſeverall kindes reſpectively are:
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Eaton.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>The Merchantaylors Schoole London.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>The Skynners at Tunbridge.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Suttons <hi>Hoſpitall.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>St.</hi> Bartholomews.</item>
                           <item>And very many other the like.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Briefly, few or no Counties of this Kingdome are unfur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht of ſuch Schooles. And ſome have ſo many, that it is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15397:18"/>diſputable whether the Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities with the Innes of Court, and Chancerie have where to receive them or no.</p>
                     <p>Some of ſuch free-Schooles againe, have <hi>Schollerſhips</hi> appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant unto them, in one of the Vniverſities or both.</p>
                     <p>To which upon Election yearely, they are removeable, As,</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>From Eaton, to Kings Colledge Cambridge.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>From Weſtminſter, to Trinity Colledge Cambridge, or Chriſt-Church Oxon:</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>From Wincheſter, to New Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Oxon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>From the Merchantaylors, to St.</hi> Iohn's <hi>Oxon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15397:18"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>And the like, from many the like.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>Some other Free-Schooles have penſions for preferment of their Schollers, and for their maintenance in the Vniverſity.</p>
                     <p>Some Companies Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate (eſpecially of <hi>London,</hi>) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no ſuch penſions in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, doe uſually out of the Stock of their Hall allow main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance in this kinde.</p>
                     <p>Beſides that, there be many other private perſons (upon my knowledge) who doe vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily allow yearely exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this nature.</p>
                     <p>Now if you would know how to finde what is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to any ſuch Free-Schooles,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15397:19"/>and in whoſe diſpoſing they now be.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Search</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In the Tower of</hi> London, <hi>till the end of</hi> Rich. <hi>the</hi> 3.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>For</hi> Grants <hi>and for Licenſe of Mortmaine,</hi> inde.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And in the Chappell of the Rolles.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>From thence till the preſent,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And for the like.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In the Regiſter of the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Court, for ſuch things devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Will, by King, Queene, or Subject,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>For ſuch</hi> Grants <hi>given by Will.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And ſometimes you ſhall finde ſuch things both in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and the <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and in the <hi>Rolls,</hi> and <hi>Prerogative</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively.</p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15397:19"/>
                     <p>For the time ſince our refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church of <hi>England</hi> began here.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Search</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Doctor</hi> Willets <hi>Synopſis,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>For all from the King, or from any other.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Search</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In divers of our Chronicles For the like.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:15397:20"/>
                     <head>Next adde certaine helpes for diſcovery and attaining thereof.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt (if it may be) procure a ſight of the Liedger Books, of ſuch as in whom the diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch things reſteth, which they keep for their owne uſe.</p>
                     <p>Next be acquainted with ſome of the Diſpoſers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                     <p>Next take the directions of the Maſter or Teacher of ſuch Free-Schooles.</p>
                     <p>Eſpecially, to be intereſſed in the Clarkes or <hi>Regiſters</hi> of ſuch <hi>Societies</hi> as have the diſpoſing of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15397:20"/>any ſuch things.</p>
                     <p>Alſo to uſe meanes by Letters of perſons powerfull, and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſuch diſpoſers.</p>
                     <p>For (indeed) it is not the ſound of a great mans name to a Letter in theſe dayes, wherein they are growne ſo common, and familiar to our Societies (of <hi>London</hi> eſpecially) can prevaile ſo ſoone as the Letter ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the <hi>Lord Maior,</hi> or other eminent Officer of the Citie, to whoſe commandement they be immediately ſubjugate.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, if you uſe the meanes leaſt ſeene, moſt uſed, and beſt allowed, together with theſe: For diſcovery and attaining of any ſuch thing, it will not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15397:21"/>be beſides the purpoſe as I take it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Now ſuppoſe your ſonne is brought to the Vniverſitie by Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or as Penſioner.</head>
                     <p>THe firſt thing you muſt take to your care is. In caſe he come not by election, but as a Penſioner, to live for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent upon your owne charge, how to procure him a Scholler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the Colledge where you beſtow him.</p>
                     <p>Or in caſe he come elected in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one, how to procure a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther addition of maintenance to him.</p>
                     <p>To bring him into a Scholler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15397:21"/>place him with a Senior fellow of the houſe (as Tutor) though you allow to ſome Iuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fellow ſomewhat yearely for reading unto him.</p>
                     <p>This Senior fellow if the number of places voide will beare it, may nominate your ſonne for one in his own right, if it will not beare it, he may call to his ayd ſome and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuffrages of the reſt as with the ſpeaking merit of your ſonne may worke your deſire.</p>
                     <p>Then how to procure a penſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for addytament of meanes.</p>
                     <p>The chiefe skill is to finde it out, being either in the gift of ſome body Incorporate, or of ſome private perſon. Wherein
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15397:22"/>the diſcovery is to be made (as aforeſaid.)</p>
                     <p>If you ſue to a Company con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of many perſons Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, you muſt enquire who be the moſt potent Patritians, and beſt reputed Veſtrie wits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, ſuch as carry their gloves in their hands, not on their hands.</p>
                     <p>Amongſt an <hi>Asſiſtance</hi> of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, onely two or three ſtrike the ſtroke, and hold the reſt in a wonderfull admiration of their extraordinary endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And how to ſpeake ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly to theſe two or three is no Myſtery. You know they are faithfull fiduciaries in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection. And therfore, you muſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15397:22"/>not preſume to offer any thing by any meanes. Onely you may deſire them to accept this poore peece of plate, with your name and Armes upon it, and binde you unto their love, in keeping the memory of you hereafter. Doe but try them in this kinde, and attend the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. I tell you, this with a Bucke at the Renter Wardens feaſt, may come ſomewhat neer to the matter.</p>
                     <p>But for the penſion to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of a private perſon, the way is not the ſame. It procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth of the givers meere chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and muſt be taken by the hand of a deſertfull receiver. Though withall it may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15397:23"/>fall out, that merit is made by mediation, eſpecially of ſome ſuch reverend Divine, as he doth moſt reſpect and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent. For other, letters can lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle prevaile with ſuch perſons.</p>
                     <p>The beſt note to diſcover a man inclinable to allow ſuch a penſion, is to examine how wealth and charity are equally and temperately mingled in him. And be ſure withall that he be a man of ſome reaſonable underſtanding in what he doth in this kinde. For a fooles penſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is like a new faſhion eagerly purſued at the beginning, but as ſcurvily left off in the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
                     <p>Your next care is, in his due
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15397:23"/>time to put on a fellowſhip, when he ſhall put off his Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerſhip, ſeeing the Schollerſhip keepes him company no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to the degree of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Arts, and a quarter of a yeere after, in thoſe Colledges, where Schollerſhips are lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt lived. And in ſome not ſo long.</p>
                     <p>In ſome Colledges, The Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip followes the Scholler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of courſe, and as the one leaveth him, the other enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines him. But in the moſt it is not ſo, but comes by Election. Which Election paſſeth by the Maſter and Senior Fellowes, whereof every one doth name one, if the number to be Elected
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15397:24"/>will beare it: or if not, then they paſſe by moſt voyces.</p>
                     <p>Where note, that the Maſter hath a double voyce, and in ſome places he hath the nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of one, if there be two places voyd, yea if there be but one at ſometimes.</p>
                     <p>In Colledges the letters of great perſons, eſpecially of the Lords grace of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Vniverſitie Chancellor have been of great prevailance. But it is not ſo now in theſe dayes.</p>
                     <p>There be beneficiall gradati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of preferment likewiſe, for Fellowes in their Colledges; as <hi>Lecturer, Deane, Bowſer, Vice-maſter,</hi> and <hi>Maſter.</hi> But for my
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15397:24"/>part, I better like and commend thoſe who when they finde themſelves fit to put forth into the world, take the firſt prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is offered unto them, rather than ſuch who live cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered like Votaries: who have Sacraments to fill up their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be it but to keep out others, ſuch as uſe no exerciſe, but wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the duſt off their bookes, and have an excellent activity in handling the foxe tayle, ſuch as hold no honour like to <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat reverentijs veſtris.</hi> And to be had <hi>Bowſer</hi> of the Colledge, as good as to be Chiefe Butler of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe preferments of the Colledge all but that of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15397:25"/>Maſter comes of courſe by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and antiquity. Therefore no meanes but patient abiding needs for the acquiring of them in their due time.</p>
                     <p>I haſten to ſend your ſonne out of the Cloyſter into the Common-wealth, and to ſhew you how many wayes of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement are open unto him abroad, with the meanes to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, and attaine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:15397:25"/>
                     <head>And firſt for the Miniſtry.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt for his eaſe, let him looke no farther than next to hand, and enquire what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices belong to their owne Colledge, and are in the gift of their Maſter and Senior fellows (as moſt Colledges have divers ſuch) and amongſt them which are void at the preſent, or whoſe incumbent is not like to live long. And if he finde out any ſuch; than if he know not after ſo long continuance among them to ſpeake in his Seniors owne <hi>Dialect,</hi> let him never tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile beyond <hi>Trumpington</hi> for me.</p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:15397:26"/>
                     <p>More indigitly, For attaining of ſuch a Benefice, let him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire where the Mattens are read with Spectacles, or where the good old man is lifted up into the Pulpit, or the like, and make a way for Succeſſion ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
                     <p>Where note, that many times a fellow of the houſe may hold ſuch a Benefice together with his fellowſhip, or a Penſion for increment of livelyhood. And ſuch tyes as theſe, are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the bond of matrimony whereby they are ſo wedded to the Colledge.</p>
                     <p>Next, he muſt climbe up to the maine top of <hi>Speculation,</hi> and there looke about him to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15397:26"/>diſcover what Benefices are emptie abroad where the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent lives onely upon the Almes of <hi>Confectio Alchermi:</hi> Or where one is ready to take his riſe out of Sierge into Sattin, out of Parſonadge and a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendarie, into a <hi>Deanarie</hi> and a <hi>Donative,</hi> let him not be ſlow of footmanſhip in that caſe by any meanes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>For Benefices abroad.</head>
                     <p>Benefices abroad are in the gift of</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The King</hi> immediately.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Or the Lord Keeper for the King.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15397:27"/>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Some Lord Biſhop,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Some Deane and Chapter:</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Some Body incorporate:</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Some Pariſh:</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Some Private Patron:</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>You ſhall finde in the Tower a collection of the Patent Rolls gathered of all Preſentations made by the King in thoſe dayes to any Church Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darie or Chappell. In right of the Crowne or otherwayes from 1. of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, till the midſt of <hi>Edward</hi> the third.</p>
                     <p>The King himſelfe onely and immediately preſented in his owne right to ſuch Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as belong to him, and are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove twenty pounds value in the <hi>firſt Fruit</hi> Bookes.</p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:15397:27"/>
                     <p>For attayning of any which I can adviſe you of no better courſe, than to learne the way to the backe ſtayres.</p>
                     <p>The Lord Keeper preſents for the King to all ſuch benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices as belong to his Majeſtie, and are under twenty pounds value in the bookes.</p>
                     <p>Now to know which of theſe are full, and who are Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bents in any of theſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Search,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The firſt Fruits Office.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Clarke,</hi> who hath the writing of the Preſentations.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Lord Keepers Secretary being.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Where note that the King hath uſed very ſeldome to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15397:28"/>grant any ſuch living in Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                     <p>And the Lord Keeper now being. His care is ſo great in this, as in all caſes of common good to provide for mans me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and cheriſh induſtry in the growing plants, that no one can offer unto him a requeſt of this kinde, without treſpaſſe to his good diſpoſition.</p>
                     <p>In the next place concerning Benefices in the Preſentation of any of the Lords Biſhops.</p>
                     <p>Note that moſt Biſhopricks in <hi>England,</hi> have preſentation to divers Benefices belonging to their Seas.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>For the number and preſent eſtate of theſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:15397:28"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Search</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Their owne Leidgers.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Their Regiſters.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Enquire of</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Their Auditors.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Their Stewards of their Courts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And ſometimes you ſhall light upon ſome of their books of this kinde, in the hands of the heyres or Executors of ſuch as have borne ſuch offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces under them.</p>
                     <p>He that is Chaplaine to ſuch a Lord Biſhop, hath for the moſt part the beſt meanes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, and opportunity, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to ſuch a Benefice.</p>
                     <p>The commendations of ſuch a great perſonage as to whom this Patron oweth greateſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15397:29"/>eſpecially for his affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in Court, may doe ſome good in the matter.</p>
                     <p>The like wayes of diſcovery, and the like meanes of attaining any Benefice in the Preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any <hi>Deane,</hi> and <hi>Chapter,</hi> are to be uſed with them reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, as with the Biſhops.</p>
                     <p>With every <hi>Deane</hi> and <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> are likewiſe divers <hi>Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries</hi> to be obtained of their gift after the ſame manner, and by the ſame meanes alſo.</p>
                     <p>The other bodies Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, beſides thoſe of <hi>Colledges,</hi> and <hi>Deanes</hi> and <hi>Chapters</hi> have many of them eſpecially of <hi>London,</hi> and ſome ſubordinate Societies thereof) right of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15397:29"/>preſentation to divers Benefices.</p>
                     <p>Alſo ſome Pariſhes by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription doe preſent to their owne perochiall Benefices. And many Patrons are content to preſent, according to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the Pariſhioners upon their hearing, and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and due exclamation of the integrity of the life of ſuch ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and no otherwiſe, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers governours, and gradati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the lands of divers Hoſpitals, and <hi>Meſons de dien</hi> have like right of preſentation to Benefices, as have other bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Incorporate. And the meanes of diſcovery and attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning are likewiſe the like.</p>
                     <p>In Pariſhes, and Companies of Tradeſmen Incorporate,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15397:30"/>ſome very few rule the roaſt.</p>
                     <p>Your Alderman of the Ward his Deputy, your Common Councell-man. Yea ſometime that petty Epitomie of Warde-mote Enquerſt, that little buſie morſell of Iuſtice (the <hi>Beadle</hi> of the Ward) will make a ſtrong partie in the election, if he be put to it. The Probotory Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, that muſt be made upon ſuch tryall before ſuch an <hi>Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie,</hi> would be according to the capacity in generall. But more eſpecially, according to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and addiction of thoſe whoſe wits the reſt have in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular reverence. As Mr. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Fiat,</hi> a good underſtanding Fiſhmonger (I aſſure you) you
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15397:30"/>may give the ſtile of right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull to them, though the beſt man of the company be but a Wine Cooper, and his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment better in <hi>Claret,</hi> than in <hi>Concioclerum</hi> a great deale.</p>
                     <p>If your ſonne upon his tryall can but fit their pallats ſmooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which is hard to doe; In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that they are ſo hollow mouthed, let him be ſure though he miſſe the Benefice for want of preperation, yet tenne to one but they will ſtraine themſelves, to bring him in as a <hi>Lecturer,</hi> which is a thing they reverence farre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Perſon of the Pariſh by many degrees.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, to private <hi>Patrons,</hi>
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:15397:31"/>and the Benefices in their gifts;</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Search,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Biſhops Regiſter:</hi> for Inſtitution, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Archdeacons Regiſter:</hi> for Induction.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Archbiſhops Regiſter:</hi> if it be a peculiar.</p>
                     <p>It was my chance lately to ſee a booke of all the Benefices within the Dioceſſe of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> with the manner of their tything in every each one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively. In which I finde, that there are, or ſhould be with the <hi>Regiſter</hi> of every Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſeven Bookes kept for En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the matters, and buſineſſe of their Dioceſſe, of which this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15397:31"/>of Benefice in the chiefe.</p>
                     <p>The like I ſaw formerly of the Dioceſſe of St. <hi>Davids,</hi> which confirmes me in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and cuſtome of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the ſaid bookes alſo in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Dioceſſe.</p>
                     <p>And ſeeing that ſeverall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate patrons are of ſeverall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, ſome more Lucrative and Covetous: Others more charitable, and religious, I can give you no other rule of attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Benefice than this, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That your ſonne bring with him ability of learning, Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of life, and conformity of behaviour, according to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Church eſtabliſht a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and theſe ſhall make his way, with the good and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15397:32"/>Patron. But for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther patron it makes no matter at all for learning, and a very little for manners, or whether he be a man conformable or no. Truely he is indifferent, for his part very indifferent.</p>
                     <p>To ſuch a Patron your ſonne muſt preſent himſelfe: thus (if he meane to be preſented) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to preſent neceſſitie. He muſt both ſpeake and prove himſelfe a man indued with good gifts. For he ſhall have to deale with a Patron of a quicke Capacity, more dexterous in apprehenſion than your ſonne or you can be in delivery.</p>
                     <p>Be this Patron what he will, your comfort is, the Benefice
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15397:32"/>muſt be fild, and that within a limited time, howſoever it is dangerous to attend the ending of the day in this caſe, (For ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome doth the Clarke of the market get any thing by their ſtanding too long and above their accuſtomed houre.)</p>
                     <p>Lapſe by reaſon of <hi>Simony,</hi> and Lapſe for not preſenting, in due time, Both offer ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement to learning. But the firſt is at hand to diſcover as a witch: And the ſecond as rare to finde out as a faithfull fiduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie or a faſt Friend.</p>
                     <p>The degrees of riſing in the Miniſtrie are not eaſier knowne than practized by the induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man.</p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:15397:33"/>
                     <p>Briefly if all Church livings in <hi>England</hi> were equally diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted, There is no one of the Miniſtry if he want not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or good manners, needs want maintenance, or good Livelyhood.</p>
                     <p>Here I could wiſh to God; That it might pleaſe the right reverend Fathers of the Church the Lord Biſhops, That they would once in every of their times cauſe a true Catalogue of all the Benefices within their ſeverall Dioceſſe with the names of the patrons thereof according to the laſt preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be ſent into the office of the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> for the better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of al ſuch as deſerve,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15397:33"/>and would gladly attaine to ſome meanes of maintenance, which they may the better doe by having recourſe thither, there to take notice of all things of this nature. For I know that many ſit downe in their wants, having good meanes to many private Patrons, onely for lacke of knowledge of the ſame.</p>
                     <p>Note that it is an uſuall thing in private Patrons to grant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and Advowſon of ſuch livings.</p>
                     <p>My ſelfe intended heretofore to collect all ſuch Benefices with their Patrons, into a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Callender for ſuch dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (as aforeſaid) and made ſome paſſage into it. But the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15397:34"/>farther I went, the more impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible I found it. And I am now reſolved that without the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops aſſiſtance it cannot be done.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And ſo much for the Miniſtery.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Lawes promotions follow</hi> BY Civill Law, and Common Law.</head>
                  <p>FOr breeding of your youth in the Civill Law, there are two Colledges of eſpeciall note
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15397:34"/>in our Vniverſities: the one is <hi>Trinity-hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridge;</hi> the other is <hi>New-Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I remember me not of any Free-Schoole in <hi>England,</hi> that have any place appendant in <hi>Trinitie-Hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi> But in new Colledge of <hi>Oxford,</hi> the Free-Schoole of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> hath claime both of Scholler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, &amp; Fellowſhips; the whole Colledge conſiſting of none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as I take it.</p>
                  <p>It is to be confeſt, the charge of breeding a man to the Civill Law, is more expenſive, and the way more painefull, and the bookes of greater number, and price than the Common Law requireth. But after the Civill
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15397:35"/>Lawyer is once growne to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity. His way of Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is more beneficiall, more certaine, and more eaſie to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, than is the Common Lawyers, and all becauſe their number is leſſe, their learning more intricate. And they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit few or no Sollicitors to trample between them and the Clyent. So that the Fee comes to them immediately, and with the more advantage.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:15397:35"/>
                     <head>The Preferments at which they arrive, are theſe:</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Chancellor to the Biſhop.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Archdeacon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Commiſſarie, where they have</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Commiſſarie. Officiall.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iudge, and Surrogate.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Advocate for the King.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mr. of the Chancerie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Kings Proctor.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Advocate, and Proctor at large.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>In theſe Courts, <hi>viz.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The High Commiſsion.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Delegates.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Prerogative.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Conſiſtory.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Arches.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:15397:36"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Biſhops Courts.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Archdeacons Courts.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Chancellors, Commiſſaries and Officials Courts.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Admiraltie Courts.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Court of the Kings Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>In times paſt.</p>
                     <p>The countenance of ſome Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, eſpecially of the L. <hi>Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> upon a <hi>Civilian,</hi> will much advance his practice as an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate, and give him promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a Iudge.</p>
                     <p>There are under the greater Officers aforenamed, divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inferiour Officers: as</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Regiſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Arctuarie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Examiner.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:15397:36"/>
                     <p>The number of the Doctors (though I finde them never to have beene limited,) Yet it is certaine that the time was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in memory of man, when the houſe of their <hi>Commons</hi> did commonly give them all ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient lodging, and dyet. And as for the number of <hi>Proctors,</hi> they were of late times limited. How it is now I know not.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:15397:37"/>
                     <head>For the Common Law.</head>
                     <p>FOr breeding of <hi>Students</hi> at the <hi>Common Law,</hi> take dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions for their <hi>method</hi> of ſtudy out of that <hi>Tractate</hi> which Mr. <hi>Iuſtice Dodridge</hi> did in his time pen for the purpoſe. Onely (for my part) I doe much commend the ancient cuſtome of breeding of the younger Students. Firſt, in the Innes of <hi>Chancery;</hi> there to be the better prepared for the Innes of Court. And this muſt needs be the better way, ſeeing too much liberty at the firſt proves very fatall, to many of the younger ſort. I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15397:37"/>and much commend al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the breeding of ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lawyers in this kinde, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That when they have beene admitted firſt into an Inne of the <hi>Chancery,</hi> they have beene withall entred as <hi>Clarkes</hi> in the office of ſome <hi>Prothonotarie</hi> of the <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> to adde the skill of the Practicke to their ſpeculation. And if a Student be thus bred, by his foundation in the one, and his experience in the other, he ſhall with more facilitie than others, who ſtep into the Inne of Court at firſt, attaine to an ability of practiſe.</p>
                     <p>Beſides other ordinary requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite parts and Arts in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15397:38"/>Lawyer. Skill in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords</hi> of all Courts of <hi>Record,</hi> and in other <hi>antiquities</hi> of Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. With ſome Reading in the Civill Law, alſo will much inable him.</p>
                     <p>The Common Lawyer is to be bred onely upon the purſe. The charge moſt at the firſt. For after he hath ſpent ſome few yeares effectually, he may attaine to the imployment of ſome private friends, for advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with, and inſtructing of greater Counſaile, whereby he ſhall adde both to his meanes, and knowledge.</p>
                     <p>It is true, that I have knowne ſome Attorneyes and Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, put on a Counſailors
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15397:38"/>gowne, without treading the ſame uſuall path to the barre (as aforeſaid.) But indeed, I never looke upon them, but I thinke of the Taylor, who in one of his Cuſtomers caſt ſuits had thruſt himſelfe in amongſt the <hi>Nobility</hi> at a Court Maske, where pulling out his Handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, he let fall his Thimble, and was ſo diſcovered, and handled, and dandled from hand to foot, till the Guard de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered him at the great Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber doore, and cryed, farewell good feeble.</p>
                     <p>If the Common Lawyer be ſufficiently able in his profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he ſhall want no practice, if no practice no profit.</p>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:15397:39"/>
                     <p>The time was that the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Counſaile had ſome ſuch helpe, as</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To be a Favourite.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A kindred.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To marry a Neece, Couſin, or a Chambermaid.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>But thoſe dayes be paſt, and better ſupply their roomes.</p>
                     <p>As fellowes of Colledges in the Vniverſities get Penſions, or Benefices, to adde to their live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hood: So Barreſters and Counſailors of the Innes of Court, advance their meanes by keeping of</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Courts of Mannors.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Leets, and Barrons:</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Swannimootes of Forreſts.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Stannaries.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:15397:39"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Cinque Ports, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>By places of</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iudges of Inferiour Courts.</hi> As</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>London, and other like Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Virdg.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Tower of London.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>St.</hi> Katherines <hi>near the Tower.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Borough of Southwarke.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Clinke.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Wentwort and like Liberties.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>By office of</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Recorder of ſome Corporate Towne.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Feodarie of ſome Counties:</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Kings Counſaile in the</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Marches of Wales, or at Yorke,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>or Iudge, or Counſaile of ſome</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Countie Pallatine:</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:15397:40"/>
                     <p>The greater places of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Common Lawyers are</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Iudges at Weſtminſter, and elſewhere:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The next, are all the ſeverall</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Officers of the Courts of Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter and elſewhere:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All which you ſhall finde ſet forth briefly in <hi>Smiths Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and part in mine owne Search of Records. And all theſe, together afford ſufficient maintenance for thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of perſons who may be here well provided for.</p>
                     <p>Here I ſhould and here I could for better direction of yonger brothers, ſhew what meniall <hi>Clarkeſhips</hi> of large exhibition,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15397:40"/>are under the great Officers of the Land, the Iudges, the <hi>Kings Counſaile,</hi> and other Officers which are not elſewhere pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht. And I know it would open a doore to many a proper mans preferment eſpecially; under the <hi>Lord Keeper:</hi> as <hi>Secretaries for Chancery</hi> buſineſſe, and Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all promotions the <hi>Commiſsion</hi> of the <hi>Peace, Iniunctions,</hi> the <hi>Dockquets.</hi> And other the like under the <hi>Lord Treaſurer,</hi> as <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries</hi> for the buſineſſe of the <hi>Realme,</hi> and the <hi>Cuſtome-houſe</hi> beſides the Inlets to ſo many preferments about the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, and Eſcheators: places, under the <hi>Lord Treaſurer,</hi> under the <hi>Chancellour</hi> of the <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15397:41"/>Dutchie,</hi> and <hi>Principality</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> and <hi>Duchie of Cornewall, as Seale keeper, Secretary, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Vnder the Maſter of the Court of <hi>Wards, as Secretarie;</hi> under the <hi>Iudges, as Marſhall, Clarke of the Bailes, &amp;c.</hi> Vnder the <hi>Barons of the Exchequer, as Examiner; Clarke of the Bailes</hi> and other Clarkes.</p>
                     <p>Vnder the <hi>Kings Attourney Generall, as Clarke of the Pattens, Clarke of the Confesſions and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Clarke of the References,</hi> Booke bearer. Vnder the <hi>Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citor Generall, Clarke of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents,</hi> Booke bearer. Beſides many other Clarkes under the white ſtaves of the Court, and in the Counting houſe, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15397:41"/>many ſeverall offices. Al which with hundreds more that I could name, with a plainer and more large deduction, were it not for fear that what I well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for general good, would be taken in offence for private pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice. But for the <hi>Clarkeſhip</hi> of the <hi>Kings</hi> houſhold, examine farther the Blacke booke in the <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Phyſitian followes.</head>
                  <p>ANd here I remember me of an old tale following, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:15397:42"/>
                  <p>At the beginning of the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py raigne of our late good Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> divers Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of great place being authorized to enquire of, and to diſplace all ſuch of the <hi>Clergie</hi> as would not conforme to the reformed <hi>Church,</hi> one amongſt others was Convented before them, who being asked whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would ſubſcribe or no, denied it, and ſo conſequently was adjudged to loſe his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and to be deprived his fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, whereupon in his impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience he ſaid;</p>
                  <p>That if they (meaning the Commiſſioners) held the courſe it would coſt many a mans life. For which the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15397:42"/>called him backe againe, and charged him that he had ſpoke treaſonable, and ſeditious words tending to the rayſing of a rebellion, or ſome tumult in the Land, for which he ſhould receive the reward of a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. And being asked whether he ſpake thoſe words or no, he acknowledged it, and tooke upon him the Iuſtification thereof; for ſaid he, ye have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from me my living, and profeſſion of the Miniſtrie, Schollerſhip is all my portion, and I have no other meanes now left for my maintenance, but to turn <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> and before I ſhal be abſolute Maſter of that Myſtery (God he knowes) how
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15397:43"/>many mens lives it wil coſt. For few <hi>Phyſitians</hi> uſe to try experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon their own bodies.</p>
                  <p>With us it is a Profeſſion can maintaine but a few. And di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of thoſe more indebted to opinion, than learning, and (for the moſt part) better qualified in diſcourſing their travailes, than in diſcerning their Patients maladies. For it is growne to be a very huſwives trade, where fortune prevailes more than skill. Their beſt benefactor the <hi>Neapolitan,</hi> Their <hi>grand Seignieur.</hi> The <hi>Sorpego,</hi> their <hi>Gonfollinere.</hi> The <hi>Sciaticke,</hi> their great <hi>Marſhall</hi> that calles the Muſter Rolle of them all together at every Spring and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15397:43"/>Fall, are all as familiar to her as the <hi>Cuckow</hi> at <hi>Cank-wood</hi> in <hi>May.</hi> And the cure of them is the skill of every good old Ladies caſt Gentlewoman, when ſhe gives over painting, ſhe falls to plaſtering, and ſhall have as good practice as the beſt of them, for thoſe kinde of diſeaſes.</p>
                  <p>Marry for Womens griefes amongſt <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> the <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine</hi> is more worthy than the <hi>Feminine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secrecie is the chiefe skill, and virility the beſt learning that is required in a Womans Phyſitian. But I never read of many of thoſe to be long lived, or honeſtly wived hitherto in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15397:44"/>all my reading.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto I ſpeake nothing in diſrepute of the more reverend, and learned ſort of <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> who are to be had in ſingular reverence, and be uſefull to mankinde next to the Divine. Indeed, I rather pitty them, and pittying ſmile to ſee how prettily theſe young gameſters <hi>Male</hi> and <hi>Female</hi> lay about them, and engroſſe the greater part of <hi>Patientrie</hi> in all places whereſoever.</p>
                  <p>And here I may more fitly ſay (God knowes) how many mens lives this abuſed <hi>opinion</hi> had of ſuch <hi>Gameſters</hi> coſts. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be not Maſters of that Myſtery, and that ſcience
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15397:44"/>which requires the <hi>Greeke</hi> tongue, exactly, all the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and skill of <hi>Philoſophie, Hiſtory</hi> of all ſorts (eſpecially naturall) knowledge of all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getatives and Minerals, and whatſoever dwels within the foure elements. Alſo skill in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomy, Aſtrology.</hi> And ſo much of the <hi>Iudicials</hi> upon all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Calculations</hi> as may be well warranted with much o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind of learning, art &amp; skil, whereof my young travailing Phiſitian, and trading wayting woman never heard.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:15397:45"/>
                     <head>Their means of Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are in theſe wayes, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>To be <hi>Phyſitian of ſome Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in one of the Vniverſities,</hi> (as divers <hi>Colledges</hi> have ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces)</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Phyſitian to the King or Queens perſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Phyſitian to either of their houſholds.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Or to ſome Hoſpitall,</hi> (as moſt have ſuch.)</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Or to ſome great perſons,</hi> who may prefer them hereafter, and be ſomewhat helpfull in the meane time.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To a good old Vſurer,</hi> or one that hath got his great eſtate toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15397:45"/>unconſcionably: For they feare nothing but death, and wil buy life at any rate: There is no coward to an ill Conſcience.</p>
                     <p>It is not amiſſe, to make way of acquaintance with Gallants given, to deepe drinking, and ſurfetting: For they are patients at all times of the yeere.</p>
                     <p>Or, a Gentlewoman that would faine uſe the meanes to be pregnant.</p>
                     <p>Or, your Laſcivious Lady, and your man in the Perriwig will helpe to furniſh with a foot-cloth.</p>
                     <p>A Citizens wife of a weake ſtomacke, will ſupply the fringe to it.</p>
                     <p>And if all faile. And the <hi>Bathe</hi>
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:15397:46"/>will affoord no roome: Let them finde out ſome ſtrange water, ſome unheard-of Spring. It is an eaſie matter to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour or alter the taſte of it in ſome meaſure, (it makes no matter how little.) Report ſtrange cures that it hath done. Beget a Superſtitious opinion in it. Goodfellowſhip ſhall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it. And the neighbouring Townes ſhall all ſweare for it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:15397:46"/>
                  <head>The Apprentice followes.</head>
                  <p>THe firſt queſtion is, to what Trade you will put your Sonne, and which is moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of choice.</p>
                  <p>For the Merchant it requireth great ſtocke, great experience in Forraine eſtates. And great ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, and adventure at the beſt.</p>
                  <p>And this is not all. For it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the Peace of our State with forraigne Princes, eſpecially thoſe with whom we hold mutuall traffique, Or, who lye in our way to intercept, or impediment our Trade abroad. Beſides that, in time of Warre
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15397:47"/>they can hold no certainty of dealing, or ſupplying their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory in parts beyond the Seas. Shipping is ſubject ever at the let goe, to be ſtayed. Marriners to be preſt, and many other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences attend them in ſuch times. Beſides the burthen of Cuſtome and Impoſition which all States impoſe more or leſſe. So that unleſſe we have peace with ſuch Neighbours, there is little hope in that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion in the ordinary and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full way of trading.</p>
                  <p>Happily you will alledge that ſome Merchants thrive well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, when the warres moſt rage, and when the ſtreame of State is moſt troubled. Some
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15397:47"/>then hold it to be the beſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing; they that gaine then (Sir) if they gaine juſtifiably: gaine not as Merchants, but as men of Warre, which occupation a man may learn without ſerving ſeven years apprentiſhip unto it.</p>
                  <p>And if they gaine juſtifiably as Merchants, it muſt be in ſome generall ſtocke of a Society in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated, who have purſe to paſſe to and fro with ſufficient power, in the moſt dangerous times. And if ſuch Societies are tollerable at any time; it is at ſuch times. How they be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe allowable, I leave to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
                  <p>For the Shopkeeper, his wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare for the moſt part, depends
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15397:48"/>upon the proſperity of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant. For if the Merchant ſit ſtill, the moſt of them may ſhut up their Shop windowes. Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Skill, Art, or Myſtery, ſhall a man learne in Shop-keeping. A man ſhall never in forraigne parts, being put to his ſhifts out of his owne Meridian, live by the skill of weighing and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring. The moſt uſe of advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage he can make of it, is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit between the Mart and the Market, than which nothing is more uncertaine, ſeeing there is no true judiciall of the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and riſing of commodities. And the caſualties that they are ſubject unto, eſpecially) in time of Warre.</p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:15397:48"/>
                  <p>Take this for a generall rule, that thoſe Trades which aske moſt with an Apprentice, are incertaineſt of thriving, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire greateſt ſtocks of ſetting up. Amongſt Trades, give me thoſe that have in them ſome Art, Craft, or Science, by which a man may live, and be a wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come gueſt to all Countries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and have imployment in the moſt ſtormy times at home, when Merchants and Shop-keepers are out of uſe: (as,)
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An Apothecarie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Druggiſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Chirurgion.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Lapidarie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Ieweller.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Printer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An Ingraver in ſtones &amp; metal.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="80" facs="tcp:15397:49"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>One that hath skill in ſeaſoning of ſhipwood.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Carpenter of all ſorts, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of ſhipping.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Smith of all ſorts, eſpecially of Clockes, Watches, Guns, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Planter, and Gardner of all ſorts.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An Enginere for making of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and the like Engines of Warre.</hi> And</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hot Preſſes for cloth, &amp;c.</hi> And</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Engines to weigh any Ship, or Guns that are drowned, &amp;c. Skrues, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A maker of all ſorts of Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for Navigation, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſes, Globes, Aſtrolabes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Drainer of grounds Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounded.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Sale-maker, and</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="81" facs="tcp:15397:49"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A maker of Cordage, Tackle, &amp;c. A Lymner.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Clothier, a Clothworker, and a Dyer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Taylor, Shooe-maker, Glover, Perfumer, &amp; trimmer of gloves</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An Imbroyderer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Feltmaker, a Glaſier, and one that can paint in Glaſſe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Briefly, any Manufacture or trade, wherein is any Science, or craft.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Onely thoſe Trades are of leaſt uſe and benefit, which are called Huſwives Trades (as <hi>Brewer, Baker, Cooke,</hi> and the like.) Becauſe they be the skill of women as well as of men, and common to both.</p>
                  <p>I would haue you know, that
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15397:50"/>the Maker was before the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taylor, and moſt Shopkeepers are but of a ſublimated Trade and retayle, but as Attorneyes to the maker. But if the Maker (without diſpute of Freedome in any Corporation, might ſet up Shop and ſell his commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty immediately) it would be a great deale better for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, than now it is.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, it is no matter of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, burthen, or diſgrace, for a Shopkeeper, yea a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, or a Gentleman, to have the skill of ſome one of theſe Manufactures, beſides his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venew, or profeſſion, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany him, what fortune ſoever may carry him into Countries unknown.</p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:15397:50"/>
                  <p>To my knowledge, a great <hi>Earle</hi> lately of this Land, did thinke it no ſcorne to indeavour the attaining of the Craft, and trade of a Farrior, wherein hee grew excellent.</p>
                  <p>And when our acquaintance tooke firſt life with thoſe of the Low Counrries, upon a Treatie wherein our Embaſſador ſtrove to ſet forth the worthineſſe of our King and Kingdome, with the Native commodities there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. The <hi>Dutch</hi> (ignorantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that no man could at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to wealth, without ſome good occupation, or manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture) askt him, what handicraft our King was brought up unto, or what trade he had uſed to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15397:51"/>get ſo much wealth withall.</p>
                  <p>I admit the Merchant Royall, that comes to his Profeſſion by travaile &amp; Factory, ful fraught, and free adventure to be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion worthy the ſeeking. But not the hedg-creeper, that goes to ſeeke cuſtome from ſhop to ſhop, with a Cryll under his arme, that leaps from his Shop-boord to the Exchange, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he is fame-falne and credit crackt, in two or three other profeſſions, ſhall wriggle into this and that, when he comes upon the Exchange, in ſtead of enquiring after ſuch a good ſhip, ſpends the whole houre in diſputing, whether is the more profitable houſe-keeping, either
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:15397:51"/>powder Beefe and brewes, or with freſh Beefe and Porridge: though (God wot) the black Pot at home be guilty of neither. And ſo he departs when the Bel rings, &amp; his guts rumble, both to one tune, and the ſame purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>The Merchant Royall might grow proſperous, were it not for ſuch poor patching interlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Lapwings, that have an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture of two Chaldron of Coles at New-caſtle; As much oyle in the <hi>Greeneland</hi> fiſhing, as will ſerve two Coblers for the whole yeare enſuing. And ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at <hi>Rowſie,</hi> for as many Fox-skins, as will fur his Long-lane gowne, when he is called to the Livory.</p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:15397:52"/>
                  <p>The Shopkeeper is a cleanly Trades; eſpecially, your Linnen-Draper, which company hath the greateſt Commonalty, and the largeſt priviledges of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and yet they maintaine nothing by Charter, for (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) they have none.</p>
                  <p>But a manufacture for my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; eſpecially, if he ſell to the wearer immediately.</p>
                  <p>Now for the better incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of men of Trade. Know that in moſt Companies of Tradeſmen incorporate (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in <hi>London</hi>) there is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion made by divers benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of their Societies decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for the enabling and ſetting up of yong beginners, by ſtocks
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15397:52"/>of money remaining in the hands of ſome few of the chiefe of their Company, (how faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſpoſed, I leave to their owne conſideration). But ſurely the poorer ſort complain much of the miſimployment of it ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally.</p>
                  <p>There is but one little Crevis to peep in at their dealings. And that is betweene their Maſters conſcience, and the Clarks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivence, which is ſo narrow, that you may ſooner diſcern the South Pole through the maine Center, than diſcover their my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</p>
                  <p>Indeed in times paſt, the Clearkſhip of the Company hath been beſtowed vpon ſome
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15397:53"/>ancient decayed member of the Company, for his livelihood. But the Attorney &amp; Scrivener; and ſome petty Clarkes of the Citie, by the Letters of, &amp;c. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>occupy thoſe places.</p>
                  <p>And here I could wiſh for righting of the dead, and relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the poorer members of ſuch Companies, who are kept in ignorance. That ſome paines were taken in the <hi>Prerogative</hi> Office, for the collating of all gifts of this nature, to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht in print, that the meaneſt might thereby be able to call their Grand Maſters to account, if they abuſe the truſt in them repoſited in this behalfe. I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the youth of mine
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:15397:53"/>age to be determined. And (God knowes) how poore a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main of life is left in my Glaſſe, yet if it may pleaſe thoſe in whom the power reſteth, to give me leave to ſearch <hi>(gratis)</hi> for all Grants and gifts of pious uſe in all kindes whatſoever. I could willingly beſtow that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of my Lampe, in collection of theſe things, and publiſh them to poſterity. Provided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, that I and mine may have the priviledge of imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame for ſome ſitting number of yeares to come.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Navigator.</head>
                  <p>NExt to the man of Trade, or rather equally with him
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:15397:54"/>I muſt give the <hi>Navigator</hi> his due for that his profeſſion is as full of ſcience; as uſefull to the Common-wealth, and as profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to himſelfe as any trade whatſoever. If he attaine the skill of knowing, and handling the tackle, the certaine art of his Compaſſe, the knowledge of languages, and diſpoſitions of forraigne Nations where he travailes and trades, he may riſe from a Squabler to a Maſter, from a Maſter to be a Generall honeſtly, and with good repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in a ſhort time.</p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:15397:54"/>
                  <p>The Navigator his way of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, &amp; imployment is, by
<q>
                        <l>The Lords of his Majeſties pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Councell.</l>
                        <l>The High Admirall:</l>
                        <l>Commiſsioners for the Kings Navy:</l>
                        <l>Chiefe of ficers of the Navyes of Societies incorporate:</l>
                        <l>Private Merchants, <hi>&amp; the like.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>With the <hi>Trinity</hi> houſe.</p>
                  <p>But if he get to be an Owner, he may trade as free as bird in ayre, as a man of warre or a man of trade, and Commerce. If he take heed that he intrench not upon the incorporated Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, eſpecially the <hi>minotaur.</hi> He cannot doe amiſſe (with Gods
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15397:55"/>aſſiſtance.) He may live merrily, and contentedly, be it but in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as a meere Carryer of home commodities. Imported from one port to another with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the kingdome.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Husbandman.</head>
                  <p>THe Husbandman may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for the happy content of the life, and the honeſt gaine which it brings with it, be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to invite a right good mans ſon to undergoe the profeſſion.</p>
                  <p>Your ſonne whom you intend for a <hi>Husbandman,</hi> muſt be of a diſpoſition part gentile, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke equally mixt together. For if the Gentleman be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant:
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:15397:55"/>his running Nagge will outrun the <hi>Conſtable.</hi> His extraordinary ſtrong Beer will be too headſtrong in office of <hi>Church-Warden.</hi> And his well mouthed dogges will make him out-mouth all the Veſtry. But if the clowne be predominant, he will ſmell all browne bread and garlicke. Beſides, he muſt be of a hardier temper than the reſt of his brethren, becauſe the unhealthfulleſt corners of the Kingdome are the moſt profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for Farmers. He muſt eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ayme at a Tenancy under the <hi>Crowne,</hi> or ſome <hi>Biſhops Sea, Deane</hi> and <hi>Chapter,</hi> ſome <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> ſome <hi>Company,</hi> ſome <hi>Hoſpitall,</hi> or ſome other body
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15397:56"/>incorporate. Wherein the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor</hi> or <hi>Receiver,</hi> muſt be his beſt Intelligencer, and Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. Young unthrifts acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance when they firſt arrive at the age of one and twenty. And good old conſcionable Landlords that hold it a deadly ſinne to raiſe the rents of their Grandfathers, or hope to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered out of Purgatory by their Tenants prayers will doe well.</p>
                  <p>Theſe profeſſions before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, be (as it were) the orbs to receive all fixed ſtars, and ſuch diſpoſitions as may be put into any certaine frame.</p>
                  <p>But for a more libertine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:15397:56"/>
                  <p>Fit it with the profeſſion of a <hi>Courtier.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For an overflowing, and Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker diſpoſition, make him a <hi>Souldier.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But beyond this he is a loſt man, not worthy a fathers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, or providence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:15397:57"/>
                  <head>The Courtiers wayes of advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be theſe.</head>
                  <p>BY the generall and moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient rule of Court, if you would have him to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto the Kings ſervice in the end. And in the meane time to have ſufficient meanes of maintenance, Place him with one of the <hi>White Staves</hi> of the Houſhold.</p>
                  <p>By the more particular rule, (if you can) put him unto the Lord High Steward his Service (who amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the white Staves) hath the chiefeſt hand in prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to any office beneath ſtayrs</p>
                  <p>If the High Steward be full, ſeek to the Lord Chamberlain,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15397:57"/>who hath the chiefe power to prefer to the places above ſtayrs, and to the Wardrobe.</p>
                  <p>And if there be no entrance there, then ſeeke to the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the Houſhold, and next to the Controller. The Maſter of the Houſhold. The Coferer, &amp; the reſt of the greene Cloth.</p>
                  <p>The Maſter of the Horſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the Avenanarie and other Clarkeſhips offices, and places about the Stable.</p>
                  <p>The principall Secretary hath heretofore had a great hand in preferring to the Clarkeſhips in the office of the <hi>Signet,</hi> and the Lord privie Seale into the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Seale office.</p>
                  <p>The Maſter of the great Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15397:58"/>into the Clarkſhips, &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices there. The Maſter of the Robes. The Maſter of the Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell-houſe, the Keeper of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Purſe. The Maſter of the Toyles and Tents with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the like have whilome bin the meanes of preferring divers their followers into the ſervice of the King, in divers beneficial places, and Clarkeſhips, in their ſeverall offices reſpectively.</p>
                  <p>The Lord <hi>Treaſurer</hi> without the houſe, prefers to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſervice, in moſt places in or about the Cuſtome-houſes, in all the parts of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And beſides theſe, I finde no meanes uſed of old, for prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into the Kings ſervice for theſe kinde of places.</p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:15397:58"/>
                  <p>The yeomen of the Guard were wont to come in for their perſonage, and activity by their Captaines allowance.</p>
                  <p>And the Bed-chamber mens fervants ever were in way to be preferred for Pages of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Chamber, or Groomes, or placed at the backe ſtaires, not of right, but of cuſtome.</p>
                  <p>For the Clarkes of the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, they were wont ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to riſe by certaine degrees, according to the preſcription of the <hi>Blacke Booke,</hi> but how it is now I know not.</p>
                  <p>For your better ſatisfaction of Court Offices, their order and Fee, Search the <hi>Blacke Booke</hi> in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> &amp; in the Court.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:15397:59"/>And for all Offices whatſoever under the King, throughout the whole Kingdome; Either in <hi>Caſtle, Parke, Chaſe, Court,</hi> or <hi>houſe</hi> of the Kings royalty or place ſoever, with the then Fees of the ſame, I referre you to a booke, Whereof many hundred Copies are extant, which was collected by the Lord <hi>Treaſurer Burleigh,</hi> and by him delivered to the late Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous memory. And ſo much for the <hi>Courtier.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:15397:59"/>
                  <head>The Souldier followes.</head>
                  <p>ANd the queſtion is firſt.</p>
                  <p>Whether the better way of thriving, is to be a Sea Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or a Land Soldier.</p>
                  <p>Queſtionleſſe the better way of thriving is to be a Sea Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, In this Kingdome of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> being an Iſland, for that he is more uſefull to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. More learning is required to be a Sea Soldier than to be a Land Soldier. A Sea Soldier is certaine of victuals, and wages; where the Land Soldiers pay will hardly finde him ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. A Sea Soldier may now and then chance to have a ſnap at a booty or a prize which may
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:15397:60"/>in an inſtant make him a fortune for ever; where the Land Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier may in an age come to the ranſacking of a poore fiſher Towne at the moſt.</p>
                  <p>More valour is required in a Sea Soldier than in a Land Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier; becauſe the extremity of the place requires it. The Sea Captaine is expoſed to as much danger during the whole fight, as the pooreſt man in the Ship, where the land Captaine uſeth but to offer his men to the face of the enemy, &amp; then retreateth.</p>
                  <p>The way to riſe to preferment at Sea, is by the <hi>Admirals</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and the <hi>Vice Admirals</hi> in the Kings ſervice, or in other ſervice by the favour of great
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:15397:60"/>traded Merchants, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of your bodies incorporate: and their chiefe Officers; and more eſpecially their Preſident, &amp; Treaſurer for the time being.</p>
                  <p>His breeding is a matter of more moment than his age re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth.</p>
                  <p>If he be true bred, he ſhould be firſt made a perfect Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor able to direct the Sterage of their courſe, able to know the tackle, and appoint every Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor to his charge. He ſhould know what number of Saylors, what Ordinance, and what mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition ſhould be requiſite for a Ship of ſuch a burden.</p>
                  <p>He ſhould be a skilfull <hi>Caneere,</hi> and able to direct the <hi>Gunner,</hi> to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:15397:61"/>ſay what quantity of powder a <hi>Peece</hi> of ſuch bore and depth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, and of what weight the bullet ſhould be where ſuch a quantity of powder is uſed, whether the <hi>Peece</hi> be ſound or hony-combed. He ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to know and direct what quantity of victuall ſhould be required for ſo many men, for ſuch a voyage. And what quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of powder and ſhot.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, to overſee and direct the <hi>Purſer</hi> and <hi>Steward,</hi> in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of their victuall without profuſeneſſe, or too much par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimony.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe skilfull in all manner of Fire-workes, and fitting En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines for ſea fight.</p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:15397:61"/>
                  <p>Briefly, he ſhould be ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, as that none ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to teach him in his place, and he skilfull to controle eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other in their places. He ſhould be courteous and loving to his men. Above all things he ſhould be zealous of the honour of God. See that the divine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice be duely read on board E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening and Morning, and that ſwearing be ſeverely puniſhed. A Sea Captaine, is not a place for a young man to leape into inſtantly, and immediately out of a Ladies Vſherſhip; a Great mans bed chamber, or a <hi>Little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> diſcipleſhip.</p>
                  <p>It is not your feathered Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant of the Court, nor your Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:15397:62"/>Roarer of the Citie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes this place I aſſure you.</p>
                  <p>I finde not any <hi>Meſon de dieu,</hi> for relieving of mayned Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners onely, but that erected at <hi>Chattam</hi> by Sir <hi>Iohn Hawkins</hi> Knight, Treaſurer of the Navy of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> wherein it was provided, that there ſhould be a deduction of Sixpence by the Moneth, out of every man and boy their wages in every voyage towards the ſame. Which I could wiſh were as well imployed as collected.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:15397:62"/>
                     <head>The Land Soldier followes.</head>
                     <p>IF the Land-Soldier thinke to thrive and riſe by degrees of ſervice, from a Common Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier to a Captaine in this age, (alas) he is much deceived.</p>
                     <p>That cuſtome is obſolete, and growne out of uſe. Doe what he can doe in Land-ſervice, he ſhal hardly riſe by his ſingle merit.</p>
                     <p>His happineſſe ſhall be but to fill his hungry belly, and ſatiate himſelfe upon a Pay day.</p>
                     <p>But if he be of kin, or a favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite to ſome great Officer, he may carry the Colours the firſt day, be a <hi>Lieutenant</hi> the ſecond, and a Captain before he knows
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15397:63"/>how many dayes goe to the week in the Regiment.</p>
                     <p>The Land-ſervice where a man may learn moſt experience of War diſcipline, is in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> by reaſon of the long exerciſe of wars and variety of Stratagems there.</p>
                     <p>Beyond that Northward, the ſervice is both more unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and more dangerous, and leſſe experience is to be there learned.</p>
                     <p>The more your Sonne turnes his face to the South, the more profitable the Land-ſervice is.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, if he have no friend or kindred to raiſe in the Land-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, I aſſure you that there is no Law againſt buying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:15397:63"/>of Offices in the <hi>Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> for ought that I have redd. Neither is it markable amongſt them.</p>
                     <p>After the Soldier returnes home, it makes no matter what number of wounds he can rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon about him.</p>
                     <p>All the wayes of reliefe for him that I can nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber are theſe:</p>
                     <p>A poore Knights place of <hi>Windſor;</hi> If the Herald report him a Gentleman, And the Knights of the Honourable Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Garter</hi> wil accept him</p>
                     <p>A Brother of <hi>Suttons</hi> Hoſpital; If the Feoffes have not ſervants of their own to prefer before him.</p>
                     <p>A Penſioner of the County; if the <hi>Juſtices</hi> finde him worthy.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:15397:64"/>And that he was preſt forth of the ſame County. <hi>S. Thomas</hi> in <hi>Southwarke,</hi> and S. <hi>Bartholomews Smithfield;</hi> only til their wounds or diſeaſes be cured and no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And that if the Maſters of the ſaid Hoſpitals pleaſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them.</p>
                     <p>For the <hi>Savoy</hi> where Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers had a foundation, I know none now.</p>
                     <p>And other Houſes appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for reliefe of Souldiers now in uſe I remember none.</p>
                     <p>For the chiefe are long ſince demoliſhed. The <hi>Templarij</hi> are gone. The Knights of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> forgotten. That fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Houſe upon <hi>Lincolne green</hi> is rac'd to the ground. And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:15397:64"/>the like now better known by the <hi>Records</hi> than the remaines of their ruins with their Revenue, are all diuerted from the uſes of their firſt foundation to private and peculiar Inheritances, which I pitty more than the diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the Monaſteries that ever were.</p>
                     <p>Here you ſee is preferment e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for your ſix Sons though you beſtow every one upon a ſeverall Profeſſion. Onely take this generall Rule for all, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To what courſe ſoever your Sons ſhall betake them. Be ſure that they al have <hi>Grammar</hi> lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the leaſt. So ſhall they be able to receive and retaine the impreſſion of any the ſaid
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:15397:65"/>Profeſſions. And otherwiſe, ſhall ſcarce poſſibly become Maſters in the ſame, or any one of them. Or if they doe, It will be with more than ordinary paines and difficulty.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Your three Daughters challenge the next place.</head>
                  <p>FOr their Portions, I ſhewed you before; how and when to raiſe them. That is, by the Marriage of your eldeſt Sonne, or out of that part of your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall eſtate which you may ſpare without prejudice of your ſelfe.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:15397:65"/>
                     <head>For their breeding.</head>
                     <p>I Would have their breeding like to the Dutch Womans cloathing, tending to profit on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and comelineſſe.</p>
                     <p>And though ſhe never have a dancing ſchool-maſter, a french Tutor, nor a Scotch taylor, to make her ſhoulders of the full breath of <hi>Briſtow</hi> Cow-ſay. It makes no matter. For wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in curious <hi>Italian</hi> purles, or <hi>French</hi> borders, it is not worth the while. Let them learne plaine works of all kind, ſo they take heed of too open ſeaming. In ſtead of <hi>Song</hi> and <hi>Muſick,</hi> let
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:15397:66"/>them learne Cookery &amp; Laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry, And in ſteade of Reading Sir <hi>Philip Sidney's Arcadia,</hi> let them read the grounds of good Huſwifery. I like not a Female Poëtreſſe at any hand: let grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perſonages glory their skill in Muſicke, the poſture of their bodies, their knowledge in languages, the greatneſſe, and freedome of their Spirits; and their arts in arraigning of mens affections, at their flattering Faces: this is not the Way to breede a private Gentlemans daughter.</p>
                     <p>If the mother of them bee a good Huſwife, and Religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed, let her haue the bringing up of one of them.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:15397:66"/>Place the other two foorth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, &amp; before they can judge of a good manly Leg.</p>
                     <p>The one in the houſe of ſome good Merchant, or Cittizen of civil and Religious goverment: the other in the houſe of ſome Lawyer, ſome Judge, or well reported Juſtice or Gentleman of the Countrey, where the Servingman is not too predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant. In any of theſe ſhe may learne what belongs to her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement, for <hi>Sempſtry, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionary,</hi> and all requiſits of Huſwifery. She ſhall be ſure to bee reſtrained of all ranke com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and unfitting Liberty, which are the ouerthrow of too many of their Sexe: there is a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:15397:67"/>pretty way of breeding young maides in an Exchange ſhop, or <hi>S. Martins le grand.</hi> But many of them get ſuch a Cricke with carrying the Band-boxe under their Apron unto Gentlemens chambers, that in the ende it is hard to diſtinguiſh whither it be their belly or their band-boxe makes ſuch a goodly ſhow and in a trade where a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſole chapman, ſhe claims ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence over her Husband, that ſhe wil not be held to give him an account of her dealings, either in retaile, or whole ſale. A Merchants Factor, and a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens ſervant of the better ſort, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not diſparage your daughters with their ſociety. And the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:15397:67"/>
                        <hi>Iudges, Lawyers, &amp; Iuſtices</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, are not ordinary Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving-men, but of good breed, &amp; their educatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the moſt part <hi>Clarkely,</hi> whoſe ſervice promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth farther and future benefit.</p>
                     <p>Your daughter at home will make a good wife for ſome Yeomans eldeſt ſonne, whoſe father will be glad to crown his ſweating frugality, with alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to ſuch a houſe of Gentry.</p>
                     <p>Likewiſe the youngmans ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers will itch to be handling of taffata, and to bee placed at the table, and to be carved unto by <hi>Miſtris Dorothy,</hi> it wil make him and the good plaine old <hi>Ione</hi> his mother, to paſſe over al reſpect of portion or patrimony.</p>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:15397:68"/>
                     <p>For your Daughter at the Merchants, and her ſiſter if they can carry it wittily, the City affords them variety.</p>
                     <p>The young Factor being fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy caught in his dayes of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and before hee travaile ſo farre into experience as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to forraigne Countries, may lay ſuch a foundation of firſt love in her boſome, as no alteration of Climate can alter.</p>
                     <p>So likewiſe may <hi>Thomas</hi> the fore man of the Shop, when beard comes to him, as Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſhip goes from him, bee intangled and belymed with the like ſprings. For the better is as eaſily ſurprized as the worſe.</p>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:15397:68"/>
                     <p>Some of our <hi>Clarkly</hi> men complaine the moyſture of their palmes. Others the <hi>Sorpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> in their wriſts, both moving meanes.</p>
                     <p>With a little patience your daughter may light upon ſome Counſailor at Law, who may bee willing to take the young Wench, in hope of favor with the old <hi>Iudge.</hi> An Attorney wil be glad to give all his profit of a <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme, Fees and all, but to wooe her through a Crevice. And the Parſon of the Pariſh being her Ladies Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, will forſware eating of tithe Pig, for a whole yeare, for ſuch a parcell of <hi>Gleb</hi> Land at all times. <hi>And ſo much for
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:15397:69"/>your Sons and Daughters.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I now eſpye mine Hoſt of the <hi>Bull</hi> here in S. <hi>Albons</hi> ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at his doore uppon his left leg, like to the old Drummer of Pariſh-garden, ready to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine us: therefore I will heere conclude with that of the Poët
<q>
                           <l>— Navibus at<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan>
                           </l>
                           <l>Quadragis petimus benevivere, quod petis hic eſt,</l>
                           <l>Eſt ang lis, animus ſi te, non deficit equais.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15397:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE MISTERY AND MISERY OF LENDING AND BORROWING.</p>
                  <p>BY THO: POWEL, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Harper</hi> for <hi>Benjamin Fiſher,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Alderſgate</hi> ſtreete at the ſigne of the Talbot. 1636.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15397:70"/>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:15397:70"/>
                  <head>THE MISTERY and miſery of Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>and Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ETTING aſide the contemplation of ſuch Lending and Borrowing, as wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſoule of Traffique is breathed into the body of a Common-wealth; I deſcend lower to that practice of mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:15397:71"/>whereby wee accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate one another for our preſent neceſſity in monies and other requiſites.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Firſt, for the Borrower.</head>
                     <p>I Will firſt ſhew who bee the moſt notable ſort of Borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Booke-men.</p>
                     <p>Next, what method every one holds in his ſeverall way of Borrowing and Booking.</p>
                     <p>Then their ſeverall cauſe of failing and inſolvency.</p>
                     <p>Next their ſundry waies and weapons; with which they fence with their Creditors.</p>
                     <p>Next, their noted places of refuge and retirement.</p>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:15397:71"/>
                     <p>Then their Jubilies and daies of priviledge.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, the certaine markes of a conſcious cautious Debtor, with the Marſhall diſcipline of the Mace, according to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne practiſe of theſe daies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Next for the Creditor.</head>
                     <p>I Will firſt ſhew the charitable extent of the Creditors cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie.</p>
                     <p>Then his Myſtery of Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</p>
                     <p>Next, how the Oyſter caught the Crow. The hand in the booke bred the wind-collicke in the ware-houſe.</p>
                     <p>And then how that winde
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:15397:72"/>being not able to force a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage through the cavernes of his credit, ſhakt the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of his ſhop-boord, threatning a moſt ſudden, ſtrange, and ſtormy eruption.</p>
                     <p>Next, the ſignes fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the wonderfull cracke.</p>
                     <p>Then the Reparation of the decaied man.</p>
                     <p>And laſtly, the ſingular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort which the Common-wealth received by him, when he was ſent forth for current out of his Creditors mint, with a new impreſſion and a ſecond edition.</p>
                     <p>And of theſe in order.</p>
                     <p>The chiefe and moſt notable Borrowers are,</p>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:15397:72"/>
                     <p>The Courtier, that neither cares for the call of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting houſe, nor the Checke of the Chamber.</p>
                     <p>The Innes of Court-men that never was ſtudient.</p>
                     <p>The Country Gentleman no Hoſpitall houſe-keeper.</p>
                     <p>The City Gallant that never arrived at his freedome by ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The Courtiours method followes.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt he invites his Creditor to a diſh of Court-Ling, with Maſculine Muſtard plenty.</p>
                     <p>Then hee ſhewes him the privie Lodgings, and the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:15397:73"/>new banqueting houſe.</p>
                     <p>Perhaps the Robes next.</p>
                     <p>Then the great Magolls tent in the Wardrope: And ſo much ſerves for the firſt meeting, and to procure an appetite to the ſecond.</p>
                     <p>To the ſecond meeting our Creditor is ſummoned, and brings behinde him his Wife, like to a broken wicker glaſſe bottle hanging at his taile, and enters into the Masking roome.</p>
                     <p>Whereat the Courtiers skill in delivering of the Maskers names, under their ſeverall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſes, did purchaſe an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting and indiſſoluble City-conſanguinity with his female charge, over whom the more
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:15397:73"/>ſleepy her ſpouſe, the more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant was my Couſen Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier.</p>
                     <p>And now hee hath made his party ſtrong enough to viſit my Citizen, and to borrow and take up of him at his owne home, in the moſt familiar phraſe that can bee deviſed for ſuch like uſe and purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>Then for the quickning, continuing, and enlargeing of of his credit, our Courtier pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends how hee has received newes that his faign'd kindred is very ſicke: and thereupon a takes occaſion (in ſtead of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſon) to ſend her bottle of that famous and farre fetcht <hi>Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineack:</hi> Hee bids himſelfe to
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:15397:74"/>dinner the ſame day, and there in a curſory way of commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the excellent art of man, in matter of Manufacture, hee fals by chance upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtuffe which hee ſaw a great perſonage weare lately in Court, not doubting but that his couzens ſhop did afford the like: His purpoſe was to have a ſuit of the ſame very ſhortly, if they would but lay it by till his moneyes come in: Yet with a very little intreaty ſo cleanly exprompted, hee was perſwaded to take it along with him, but onely for feare leſt the whole peece might be ſold by the fooliſh fore-man
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:15397:74"/>unawares before his returne.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Give us old Ale and booke it,</l>
                        <l>O give us old Ale and booke it:</l>
                        <l>And when you would have your money for al</l>
                        <l>My couzen may chance to looke it.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The Innes of Court-man, and his method.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt hee makes himſelfe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Creditor, by going to him in company with one who is a knowne cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomer there, and an approved good pay-maſter.</p>
                     <p>Then hee procures this knowne cuſtomer to take the man of credence (as it were) modeſtly apart, and at his backe
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:15397:75"/>while hee is walking downe the ſhop and averſed, to whiſper: That this gentleman whom you ſee heere, is ſon and heire to that worthy Knight ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in the Peake, or that moſt markable Malſter of much Marlborne: or the great Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier of Grims borow, or the like. Then he returnes to the upper end of the ſhop, and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter takes an occaſion to call to <hi>Thomas</hi> to give the Gentleman a ſtoole, and tels him that hee knowes his friends very well: The ancient Mannor houſe, and the Mill, and goodly medowes a little beneath in the bottome: adding further, that no doubt but if hee pleaſe the good old
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:15397:75"/>Gentleman, hee may in time bee owner of them all him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Bee owner; ſaies my Innes court man. Why I tell you, that Water-mill came by my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with all the Meddowes of that Levell: And my Father would hang himſelfe hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give them away from mee.</p>
                     <p>And whereas you ſay I may be owner in time, I thinke the old man has held them long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: unleſſe you would make his time endleſſe, and him a very wandring Jew. I wis my Grandfather ſerv'd not him ſo, hee knew what he did when he dyed. Hee did it out
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:15397:76"/>of true judgement, in fulneſſe of underſtanding, able to penne his owne will himſelfe, when he was no longer ſerviceable to his Countrey, hee would not live onely to mend the fire, or preſerve it by applying every circumſtant cinder within his reach: but though I pinch for it awhile, a time (I hope) may come.</p>
                     <p>Whereat my Creditor inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting him, ſaies, alas you pinch for it? That ſhall not need) God be thanked) your credit it worthy to be rankt in a ſhop booke, cheeke by jowle with any debitory diſpoſed Gentleman of this towne what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. Beſides, if you would
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:15397:76"/>bee loath to have your name extant in ſo publicke a Reper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, you are able by ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate as is inſeparably annexed to your perſon, to give farther aſſurance (I doe but ſpeake it if neede were) by otherwaies, and otherwiſe at your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
                     <p>Further aſſurance (replies my Gallant) A pox on't For aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance they ſhall have what they will: And for price of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, it is my deſire they ſhould gaine by mee, yea they ſhall gaine by mee: For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe how ſhould you be able to live by it?</p>
                     <p>Now ſir, you ſpeake like an honeſt gentleman (ſaies hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine)
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:15397:77"/>gaine) I would al our cuſtomers were of your minde, there bee too few ſuch as you are; if you have neede of any thing heere, either for your wearing, or elſe for converſion, wherein I hope you conceive mee ſir, it is at your command.</p>
                     <p>Hereupon the man of the ſword ſweares that he ſhall not out-doe him in nobleneſſe: Had hee robbed the Statuaes of the new Standard of all their roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all reſolutions. Hee vowes to returne thither againe, and that ſpeedily to bring his Tailor with him adviſedly: to take up for divers uſes with much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility, and to give aſſurance ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the direction of his
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:15397:77"/>owne Scriviner, a Bow lane moſt legally.</p>
                     <p>And ſo leave we him like a horſe put up to dyet, whereby to bee prepared to runne his traine ſents on the deepeſt ground of aſſurance, that City counſell can finde out or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Puppy runnes well, but who ſhall winne the day.</l>
                        <l>Puppy? or Noddy? 'Tis an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven lay.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="138" facs="tcp:15397:78"/>
                     <head>The Country Gentleman his Mothod</head>
                     <p>THe Countrey Gentleman, he is by this time come up to London; and has brought his Atturney with him, one that profeſſes the taking up of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by writ of right. His Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny brings him to the Ship be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Exchange, and leaves him there while hee goes to fetch the onely <hi>Noverint</hi> in in thoſe parts, whom hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares at his ſhop with the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, adviſing him withall in his eare, ſo to handle the matter in hall, that beards may wag all, which hee delivered with a
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:15397:78"/>moſt familiar wringing of him by the hand, to inſinuate his meaning as unto his ſhare: Hee then brings the Scrivener unto the taverne, good compliance is in all parties, and the Scrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner according to the true pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of moſt of them, at the firſt meeting, eſpecially while they are with the borrower in the taverne, was more eaſie in promiſing, then they in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing.</p>
                     <p>The Atturney then ſoftly tels the Gentleman apart, that hee ſhould doe well to beſpeake ſupper inſtantly, aſſuring him that if he could but faſten that courteſie upon the Scrivener for the preſent, hee were their
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:15397:79"/>owne for ever after, neither the ſumme nor the ſecurity could bee matter of any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty.</p>
                     <p>The counſell was held whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome as unto the ſupper, the Atturney was forthwith pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd to the Bar, where he ſpake ſo learnedly in the cauſe, that upon the ſame hearing they recovered three full diſhes on their ſide, the boyes drew the proceeding of the buſineſſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Clarke-like, the Kirchin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid ſupplied with the Tales. The Miſtreſſe call'd earneſtly for the Poſtea, and the Maſter he rated and allowed the bill of coſts.</p>
                     <p>At the execution whereof,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:15397:79"/>my Scrivener fearing leſt the ſhot ſhould diſperſe and ſcatter it ſelfe amongſt them, while the Gentleman was feeling for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to diſcharge it; he to facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate that hand, askes him ſoftly in his care; <hi>What is the ſumme that he would have?</hi> Then ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the long dwelling of his hand in his pocket, hee tels him, <hi>He ſhall have what ſumme he will:</hi> Let mee ſee, faies the Scrivener, there comes in this night of Sir <hi>Samvan Skynkers</hi> money, five hundred, and to morrow as much more I can ſupply you from one hundred to ten out of that as your occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions require: how ſay you?</p>
                     <p>Wee will have no dry recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:15397:80"/>replies the Gentleman: Heer's the full ſumme of the bil and and a pottle over; though wee be Leiceſter-ſhire fed, yet we be not Brackly bred, I aſſure you.</p>
                     <p>And for the ſumme which I ſhould (or at leaſt would have) for eſpeciall occaſions, Let me ſee: there is a horſe-race at Northampton on Munday come ſevenight: I muſt needs have new furniture for Crop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care, which I will ſend downe by Leiceſter Waggon.</p>
                     <p>I wil have that Hawke which I ſaw in Southwarke this after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone: clothes would doe wel: but thats my leaſt care of a thouſand. A poxe a pride I ſay.</p>
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:15397:80"/>
                     <p>Howſoever I muſt ſee the party I told you of by the way, before I goe out of towne, by any meanes if ſhee keepe the ſame lodging &amp; the ſame name that ſhe was wont to doe: thats all now. Lets ſee, a matter of ſome three hundred will doe't ſo far forth as my preſent and moſt urgent occaſions do preſſe me at this inſtant:</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>As for payment,</l>
                        <l>And for raiment,</l>
                        <l>For hedges and mounds,</l>
                        <l>And ſtocking of grounds,</l>
                        <l>For Corne for ſeed,</l>
                        <l>Or Cattle to breed,</l>
                        <l>Or the Wolfe at the doore,</l>
                        <l>And a thouſand things more.</l>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="244" facs="tcp:15397:81"/>
                     <p>They are nothing ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant and concerning as the leaſt of theſe: I would not miſſe Munday come ſevenight for three ſuch ſummes, I tell you Sir: Munday come ſevenight! That were a jeſt indeed.</p>
                     <p>For that and what you pleaſe beſide, ſaies the Scrivener, you ſhall find no default on my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: This honeſt Gentleman that is with you knowes the courſe of theſe kinde of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: He and I ſhall take my leave at this time.</p>
                     <p>The Scrivener departs, and the Gentleman ſtaies behinde, onely to hugge and endeare the endowments of him that procured this meeting: Hee
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:15397:81"/>praiſes the proſperity of their journey, commands the comely carriage of the Scrivener, and vowes everlaſting acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of his Atturnies acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity. And ſo they betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their lodging likewiſe for that night.</p>
                     <p>The next morning my gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſends his Atturney to ſee that the money which he ſpake for, be told out and made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for him againſt his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, which ſhould be when and where it ſhall pleaſe the honeſt Scrivener. (For by this time hee had attained ſo much of reputation among them.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day and the next were both ſpent in continuall
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:15397:82"/>queſt of the Scrivener. But the Boyes in the Shop according to their maſters direction made anſwere, one while that he was gone to Sir <hi>Sam</hi> for monies: Another while that hee was at the ſealing of writings at ſuch a place: Then that he was at the ſpeeding of a Commiſſion of Bankeruptiſme at Guild-hall, God bleſſe the place, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good man of the Grand Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: And then ſhortly after, that he was but even now gone forth, and that it was impoſſible but that he ſhould meete him, unleſſe the duſt of Popes-head Alley had put out his eyes by the way.</p>
                     <p>The time weares out, and the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:15397:82"/>horſe-race comes onward, the apprhenſion whereof puts our Gentleman into ſuch a perpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that on the next day early in the morning he goes to the Scriveners ſhop, where ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unawares hee findes him ſaying his prayers, while hee was withall croſſe gartering of himſelfe: and had he not known him better by his croſſe-garters then by his prayers, queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he had loſt his labour.</p>
                     <p>Good morrow (ſayes the Gentleman) perhaps I doe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbe your devotion?</p>
                     <p>You Raſcall, how chance you doe not hang out the Labells? (ſaies the Scrivener to his boy) Then hee proceedes with his
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:15397:83"/>prayers, and ſuddenly beſpeaks the Gentleman, asking, What is your will with me Sir? Have you any buſineſſe with me I pay now?</p>
                     <p>O Lord Sir, (ſaies he) I hope you remember what paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene us at the Ship on wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday night laſt, touching the three hundred which I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to have the next morning, parcell of the thouſand which was to come in then</p>
                     <p>Hum (ſaies the Scrivener) I thinke there was ſome ſuch matter: I remember wee tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of it: But what were the names of your ſecurity which you did then give me.</p>
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:15397:83"/>
                     <p>For names (replies he) why I gave you none, for I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it ſhould not need: Or if it doe, you ſhall have lands and that for ſeat and ſite, value, and Virgine title, ſhall beare and ballance your morgage downe to the center.</p>
                     <p>Now you come to me (ſaies the Scrivener) goe you to the Antwarp, but onely to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare mee a particular of this land, and I wil be with you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently.</p>
                     <p>They goe before the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular is made ready. The wine is burnt, the Scrivener with much paine has paſt through his prayers, and recovers the Taverne doore, by that time he
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:15397:84"/>was come to <hi>(Amen.)</hi> He returns to his old complement, pockets the Particular which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him, and puts all unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe into this cup; He drinkes freely, and promiſes nobly: So that now there was no doubt made but we might be at Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton moſt opportunely. And ſo much for that meeting.</p>
                     <p>After dinner they came both againe to the ſhop; where they found my Scrivener wrapt warme in his gowne about him, faſt aſleepe (good man.) For if ever he were good, he was then good: Or (at leaſt) I am ſure he was then and there at the very beſt of Scriveners good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; the height of their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:15397:84"/>and the perfection of their punctuality.</p>
                     <p>They muſt by no means trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him before he bee fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered and enabled for a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond meeting at the Mermaid after Exchange time. They attend the while: the clouds of Claret ſhortly ſpend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: he wakens, they ſalute him.</p>
                     <p>At length with much a doe he cals them to remembrance, and askes them for their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular: they ſhew the errour in his pocket, and ſo hee promiſes their diſpatch the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning without any faile, and they are gone to be ſpeake furniture for Cropeare in the meane
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:15397:85"/>time. At the appoynted houre my Atturney comes to know if the writings were ready to ſeale, and the mony proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into ſeverall hundreds, in ſo many ſeverall bagges or no.</p>
                     <p>The Scrivener replies, that it ſhould bee forth with prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red accordingly, ſo as they ſhould bring good Citty ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with them, but onely to undertake for the property and tranſparancy of the title of the Lands ſo tendred, and that was all ſhould neede for the matter, procuration being over provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, and writing taken to eſtimation according to the repute of the place where it was to bee written, and that
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:15397:85"/>was all that was now remaining to bee conſidered of on the Gentlemans behalfe. This new taske required more time in poſſeſſing and perſwading ſome Citizens his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who knew him and his Lands ſo well, that it was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable, whether was more deare and deſired unto them.</p>
                     <p>They joyne with him in the ſecurity, and become immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately bound with him by bond for the payment of the money at a certaine day to come, and to the great amazement of the Scrivener, thanke him for this counſaile in adviſing and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them to the cautionary cauſe-way of ſecurity both
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:15397:86"/>latterally &amp; collaterally, by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and oblique lines which he moſt methamatically had ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined &amp; contrived in his head, as well for his owne commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity as for their indempnity, without demanding of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſſurance as yet, and ſo my Gentleman is diſpatcht without further tie upon Lands or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hitherto, ſaving what is mentally reſerved upon the growth of this ſumme; by theſe his loving friends and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Friendſhip for countries ſake I doe commend</l>
                        <l>But not to ſell my countrie for a friend.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:15397:86"/>
                     <head>The Citizen, a Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onary Freeman, his <hi>Method.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe laſt, but not the leaſt of theſe, is our City borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, a hopeful yongman (though I ſay it:)</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>A man of wiſedome, for hee is the beſt</l>
                        <l>That ere was of our Ward-moot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt:</l>
                        <l>Of ſweete behaviour, for this very yeere,</l>
                        <l>He hath diſcharg'd the place of Scavenger.</l>
                        <l>At an arbitrement he is a Cutter,</l>
                        <l>As ere concluded in a Tavern ſupper.</l>
                        <l>If Females for their linnen doe contend,</l>
                        <pb n="157" facs="tcp:15397:87"/>
                        <l>He takes up all, and makes a friendly end.</l>
                        <l>And if our Veſtry brethren do diſſent,</l>
                        <l>he makes the elder head moſt eminent</l>
                        <l>Grow up thou man of iuſtice, and of hope,</l>
                        <l>My pen gives thee thy due, give thou it ſcope.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>Now this youth, not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether free by Patrimony, but partly by Matrization, is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull cautious of being a bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower upon Record, or in the eye of the World. He wil not have his name tendred unto a Scrivener by any means, while hee is yet but eaſily declining upon the ſtreame of ready mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and not in ſtocke, like the water which though it fall and ſinke by the ſides, yet runnes up
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:15397:87"/>in the middeſt with a manifeſt current long after.</p>
                     <p>Hee now ſtudies how to take up without expreſſion to bee a principall for himſelfe, or to be too promptly drawn into ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for others. Hee finds out for property for this purpoſe a young heire, who for a third ſhare of the ſumme, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to beare the only name and blam of Borrower, and to yeild to the enſafing of my Citizen, by ſuch Counter-bonds, ſales, and aſſignements, as by the <hi>Scrivener</hi> and himſelfe, could bee deviſed to uphold the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of a wonderfull wary man.</p>
                     <p>Can you now cal this man
<pb facs="tcp:15397:88"/>a Borrower for doing his friend a courteſie? Or is this man in a declenſion, when it appeares by the booke, that he is in the way of purchaſing? No ſuch matter, this cries up his credit: And howſoever theſe monies be repayd, yet hee is ſure of the Land, which before any inſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency ſhall appeare on his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, hee does intend to convey over in truſt ſecretly, to the uſes of his lively-hood for the time of reſtraint to come, and like one that prepares his tomb while he is yet living, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves what lodging to take up on the Maſters-ſide, when his credite ſhall depart this Mortall life.</p>
                     <pb n="159" facs="tcp:15397:88"/>
                     <p>Beſides, hee had another way of borrowing, he findes out an old Uſurer of the ſame Pariſh, Father to divers daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, who catcht at Eſpouſall preferment, onely by their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers countenance, and their conciſe carriage.</p>
                     <p>The one of theſe hee ſingles out from the Heard, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends moſt pure and unfaigned love unto her: He viſites her in his gown at <hi>Midſummer,</hi> where at the old man conceives great joy and comfort, glories in his gravity, and delights in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency. Hee on the other ſide perceives the powle-cat in the purſe-net, makes preſent uſe of it. He ſhewes him the convei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:15397:89"/>which the Heire made the other day unto him of all the houſes in Conny-hoope-lane a one ſide; and deſires to bee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht by him with ſo much as might bring the other ſide into his property likewiſe: for that it was now offered unto him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reaſonable conditions, ſo ſhould he reduce all (as it were) into a circle, and his daughter ſhould hold that for her joynter and have the Evidence in her owne cuſtody.</p>
                     <p>The old man lik't this paſſing well, and for feare leaſt the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine ſhould bee ſnatcht out of his hand, he takes him into his cloſet, tels out the Monie, and ſends him away inſtantly.</p>
                     <pb n="161" facs="tcp:15397:89"/>
                     <p>The old man turnes him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and (poynting at her ſweet heart) beſpeakes his daughter thus:</p>
                     <p>There goes hee that labours for you moſt induſterouſly, ſtudious your good right care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, I pray God make you thankfull for him accordingly: For you ſhall have an Husband (be it not vainely ſpoken) that for thrift and Husbandry may be the very browch of of al the City.</p>
                     <p>In ſtead of going forthwith unto his Chapman, for the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and candle rents, he is hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed preſently at a widowes in the way, where hee ſpends his time till candle-light.</p>
                     <pb n="162" facs="tcp:15397:90"/>
                     <p>Here he likewiſe proteſts and profeſſes love by whole-ſale; he ſhewes her the monies, and tels her what a bargine hee could now have, if ſhe would joyne ſtocke with him in ſuch a commodity come lately into the Downes with the laſt Eaſt-Indian ſhips. It might pleaſe God that this might bee a happy occaſion of uniting their perſons as well as their parcels together.</p>
                     <p>The Widow was hereupon taken with ſuch a Sorpego in her wriſts, that her fingers ends itcht to be teſting out of her part, and to take iſſue upon his promiſe of the union, which ſhe performed with much dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
                     <pb n="163" facs="tcp:15397:90"/>
                     <p>Then he puts altogether, and aſſures her that hee will bee gone the next tide to Graveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end,</p>
                     <p>When hee comes home, hee diſpatches letters ſpeedily to the old uſurer, certifying him of his good progreſſion in Cony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoope-lane, and deſiring his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience for certaine dayes, which the contriving of his aſſurance by good and ſufficient counſell would take up.</p>
                     <p>The time pretended for the Downes, and to draw downe a good eſtate for his young Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, is upon better conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration beſtowed at <hi>Rumford,</hi> where whoſoever had ſeene him in the lift of his liberality<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        <pb n="164" facs="tcp:15397:91"/>would little thinke him to be ſo little a thing as might be contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within the compaſſe of a Counting-houſe, or bee confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within the proſpection of a falſe light.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Expect anon the ſequell of his ſtory.</l>
                        <l>Let <hi>Rumford</hi> now be famous for <hi>John Dory.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Their ſeverall cauſe of inſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency followeth.</head>
                  <p>THe Courtiers cauſe is in his conſcience: For he neither can, nor cares to pay.</p>
                  <p>The Innes of Court mans cauſe is in his Coercence, for
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:15397:91"/>he would if hee could pay.</p>
                  <p>The Countrie Gentlemans cauſe is in his confidence, for he truſts to his Country men of the City, and had rather they then he ſhould pay.</p>
                  <p>But the Cittizens cauſe is in his complacence.</p>
                  <p>It pleaſeth him ſo to pay, and he ſees no reaſon why he ſhould goe beyond the rule of defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
                  <p>Hee findes good grand Jury Preſidents of five ſhillings in the pound, and it is faire too and ſufficient ſoder for the firſt flaw (by my faith.)</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Some would and if they could:</l>
                     <l>Some can, and yet they care not:</l>
                     <pb n="166" facs="tcp:15397:92"/>
                     <l>The leaſt pay what they ſhould:</l>
                     <l>The moſt ſpend all and ſpare not.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ſundry wayes and weapons with which they fence with their Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, challenge the next place.</head>
                  <p>THe longeſt weapons with which my Courtier keeps his creditor fartheſt off, are the winters journeyes, and the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers progreſſe.</p>
                  <p>And when he is neerer hand, hee doth keepe them at ſtaves length, by challenging of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy for indiſpoſition of body, conference with great and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable perſonages, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:15397:92"/>in the States won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull weighty affaires, when (God wot) the indiſpoſition is for want of cleane linnen.</p>
                  <p>The conference is with his boy, how to pay the Landreſſe which detaines it.</p>
                  <p>And his imployment is in and about the taking of a pipe of Tobacco.</p>
                  <p>The privy watergate, and the garden out-let doe well.</p>
                  <p>And when hee findes no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, but that his Creditor wil cloſe and come into him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his weapons length, then hee ſweares that hee was even now about to ſend for him, had hee not prevented him.</p>
                  <p>He tels him in great ſecreſie
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:15397:93"/>how he is in poſſibility to paſſe a ſuit of great worth, onely hee wants ſome money to ſcatter in fees by the way: For it is to be underſtood, that with great Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers the Chamber men weare good clothes, &amp; the doorkeeper has a pretious faculty: hee ſhall onely ſupply with ſo much as will even the old ſumme, and pay himſelfe, <hi>tot, talia,</hi> and <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taa,</hi> at his owne pleaſure, yea he ſhall be a <hi>Patentee</hi> himſelfe, for argument of honeſt purpoſe and honourable dealing.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>What ſhift ſo ere we make, hee needs muſt doe it.</l>
                     <l>For profit and preferment pricke him to it.</l>
                  </q>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:15397:93"/>
                     <head>The Innes of Courts mans weapons</head>
                     <p>HIs firſt weapon is a wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd Letter, excuſing his delay by incompetency of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition.</p>
                     <p>Or by the neceſſity of atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the revolution of their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants ſixe monthes day of pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according to the cuſtome of the country.</p>
                     <p>But eſpecially by occaſion of his fathers great and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſickneſſe (though there were no ſuch matter) for that he knew was the only viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couſe matter to belime his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor that could bee deviſed or applyed.</p>
                     <pb n="170" facs="tcp:15397:94"/>
                     <p>The next weapon, when the former way is ſtale of aſſiduity, is his good ſword, a watchfull eye and a ready hand.</p>
                     <p>The laſt is the deviation and avoyding of the moſt frequented paſſages and ſtreets, and to hold compaſſe at the halfe point, through the Let-goes of Allies, Tavernes, with backe-doores, or by water, as ſtands wit moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>His fencing in the night I moſt commend,</l>
                        <l>When hee may ſafely drab, and drinke, and ſpend.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="171" facs="tcp:15397:94"/>
                     <head>The Country Gentleman his weapons.</head>
                     <p>THis youth (alas) hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion at the firſt to practiſe his defence, or knowes the uſe of the weapon, nor will he bee brought to it of a long time; when payment is prefixed to be made to him the ſaid <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſet in ſilver ſtreet London, hee in his better wiſedome is betting of all his white money at the Cock-pit in Coventry.</p>
                     <p>And when all comes to all, when farther occaſion hath drawn him into a farther reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuality with his undertakers in London; ſo that he muſt either
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:15397:95"/>ſtand upon his guard; or loſe the Bleane, with all meadowes, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, feedings, woods, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woods, and other the appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances worth tenne times the mony borrowed.</p>
                     <p>Then, O then, hee lookes out his manly munition.</p>
                     <p>The ancient ſleeping entaile.</p>
                     <p>The old mother joyncture.</p>
                     <p>The endowment of his wife, <hi>ad oſtium Eccleſiae.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Al theſe he brings to his Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of Chancery-lane, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes ſo much upon the oyle of equity, and will ſcoure them up cleanly, and make them fit weapons of defence againſt al the coſſaques of the City.</p>
                     <pb n="173" facs="tcp:15397:95"/>
                     <q>
                        <l>Petitions bee the poſtures of thy guard,</l>
                        <l>And may thy motions bee like Canons heard;</l>
                        <l>Set field, or skirmiſh, Chamber, or the Barres,</l>
                        <l>Tis like to prove a very lingring warre.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The City borrower his fence.</head>
                     <p>HE handles his weapon with the beſt grace of them all, his Creditor dares ſcarce come within his reach, but onely aske how hee does as hee goes by. And if he doe preſume to leave word with the apprentice boy, that he would have him tel his maſter that he was here to ſpeak with him about the other buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, it is a very bold adventure,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:15397:96"/>and a ſawcy preſumption taken very cenſoriouſly by my young maſter, at his comming home, eſpecially if he have bin at the Renterwardens feaſt, the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties occaſion the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, &amp; the parochical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion: theſe be the things that challenge propriety and priori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in a comely Citizen, before all other reſpects whatſoever. He wil not diſcontent the firſt, nor diſapoynt the ſecond, nor disfurniſh the laſt for obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of whomſoever.</p>
                     <p>For the mony taken up of the Scrivener, the intereſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly needes to be paid in as yet: and the Scrivener (to ſtop his mouth) hee ſhall have the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:15397:96"/>and benefit to eject the Tenants of Cony-hoop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane, and withall hee will have the Scrivener ſue the bond both againſt the heire and himſelfe, upon which he will appeare to ſuffer judgements againſt both right willingly. (Marry) he ſhal take execution againſt the heire onely.</p>
                     <p>For the old Uſurers mony, he found that the aſſurance could not be perfected til the next Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chalmas terme, for it required the ceremony of the barre, and before hee would debarre his wife of any ceremony belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to her, he would bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted the unperfecteſt member that ever miniſtred in the Cities myſteries.</p>
                     <pb n="176" facs="tcp:15397:97"/>
                     <p>And for the Widowes money beſtowed in the Downes, hee found the commodity not ſo vendible here as beyond the ſeas, therefore hee thought it beſt to ſend it into Holland, where it attends the next mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, and would not ſo much as ſuffer it to touch at our coſt.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>This cannot cure but lengthen thy diſeaſe,</l>
                        <l>It may deferre the paine, but not releaſe.</l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Their noted places of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge and retirement followes.</head>
                     <div type="place">
                        <head>Ram-Alley.</head>
                        <p>I Will not ſo much as looke in to the Court, or any the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding houſes; the Houſe-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:15397:97"/>lodging, nor the Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners receit, neither the Mewes. Nor prye into the meniall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of any of the Innes of Court, farther then they ſtand for refuge and reliefe of the neighbouring priviledges about them.</p>
                        <p>The firſt and chiefeſt of all which, for advantage of the ground, for Fortifications, for water-workes, poſternes and paſſages, ſupplies, and proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Land or otherwiſe, is that ſo farre fam'd, &amp; ſo fitly nam'd <hi>Ram-alley,</hi> or the <hi>Ramy-kins,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording unto the Dutch tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                        <p>In it is a <hi>garriſon</hi> of olde ſouldiers, every one of the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:15397:98"/>which is able to lead a whole arwy of younger debtors.</p>
                        <p>They call their Muſter-role in the round Church: they drill them in the Garden, and they make their ſet battailes under the trees in the new walkes, which peece of ground was li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in, and level'd for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
                        <p>For the workes within <hi>Ram-Ally,</hi> there be 2 moſt notable: the one is rais'd &amp; contrived in the forme of a <hi>Ram,</hi> which <hi>Rams</hi> were uſed in the old <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, as appeares by the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory it ſelfe more at large.</p>
                        <p>This worke is of a reaſonable ſtrength, having a watch-tower in the ſimilitude of a Coblers
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:15397:98"/>ſhop, adjoyning, from whence all the forces about are called together upon the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the enemy.</p>
                        <p>But the other is a fort moſt impregnable, where the enemy dares not ſo much as come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhot, to take the leaſt view of it.</p>
                        <p>There is none but this onely one ſo invincible, far and neere: and therefore our latter writers have ſtiled it the <hi>Phoenix.</hi> There be other pretty contrived plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes in the faſhion of the Cookes-ſhops two or three, where if a Setter or Spy doe but peepe in at them, they will make him pay for the Roaſt before hee
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:15397:99"/>depart (Ile warrant him.)</p>
                        <p>To the Rammy kins doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long a very great fleete, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of many ſaile well man'd, and theſe are onely for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice by water.</p>
                        <p>This place according to the Geographicall map, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of our moderne Authors, cannot poſſible be ſo beſieged, but that they within may go in and out at their pleaſure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out impeachment.</p>
                        <p>At the Middle-temple gate they iſſue in ſpite of the Divell.</p>
                        <p>At the Inner temple gate they feare no colours in the Raine-bow.</p>
                        <p>And at <hi>Ram-Alley</hi> Poſtern, in caſe they cannot fetch Fetter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:15397:99"/>but diſcover ambuſhment, they need onely draw their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies within guard of pike, turn faces about, and retreat through the Miter.</p>
                        <p>Or admit they ſtand for Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet, &amp; be ſo intercepted, that they can neither recover the Miter, nor <hi>Ram-Alley,</hi> it is no more but onely to mend their march, fall downward as if they gave way, ſuddenly diſcharge their right hand file, and fall ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily into Serjeants Inne, where by ancient treaty had betweene theſe two houſes, it was agreed that the parties in ſuch diſtreſſe might, paying the welch Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle man porters Fee; haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy and conveyance thorough
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:15397:100"/>the Garden into the temple without re-hazzard of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
                        <p>Likewiſe when they would Forrage, they are no ſooner out of the Middle-temple-gate, but there be three ſeveral places of defence to friend them: <hi>(viz.) The Bell Inne:</hi> the Bar-gate, and Shire lane. And the paſſage through the Kings bench office is a moſt excellent ſafe way for cloſe contriving and retriving.</p>
                        <p>The Gardners war fage as the tide may ſerve, wil ſerve the turne too.</p>
                        <p>But the new doore by the Bochards, though it be none of the ſweeteſt way, yet it is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of al the reſt, for at the ſight
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:15397:100"/>of the pompe the ſetter ſtarts backe, and will by no meanes purſue him any further.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="place">
                        <head>Fulwoods Rents.</head>
                        <p>THe next place of refuge is is commonly called <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woods Rents,</hi> which lies ſo in the maine and plaine continent, that it requires the ſtricter watch, and ſtronger court of guard to be kept about it.</p>
                        <p>Beſides, the Generall of the enemy hath planted very neere it, and lately caſt up a mount in the faſhion of a Shriefes Office juſt in the face of them. In <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woods Fort,</hi> otherwiſe yeklee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped <hi>Skink-skonce,</hi> beſides <hi>Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> &amp; his out-lawes, like a regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Tailors,</hi> the one halfe
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:15397:101"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="183" facs="tcp:15397:101"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="184" facs="tcp:15397:102"/>with red beards, and the other having no beards at all.</p>
                        <q>
                           <l>Captaine Swanne was a very tall man,</l>
                           <l>So was not Francis Drake a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>;</l>
                           <l>When Srypp does ſweare in ſingle Beere,</l>
                           <l>The Bailiffes uſe to quake a.</l>
                        </q>
                        <p>At the upper end of theſe rents and at the very portall of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poole-palace weſtward, was lately begun a moſt excellent peece of worke, which had it not beene interrupted by thoſe that playd upon them from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, (queſtionleſſe) it had bin the very ſtrongeſt and ſureſt hold that ever was rais'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the contine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for this purpoſe.</p>
                        <p>The backe gate into Graies Inne lane, with the benefit of the little Alley, <hi>ex oppoſito,</hi> is of good uſe, but not at all times.</p>
                        <pb n="185" facs="tcp:15397:102"/>
                        <p>The paſſages through certain Innes on the field-ſide, are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted with ſome hazzard by reaſon of the ſtragling troopes of the enemy who lye pardue in every Alehouſe thereabouts.</p>
                        <p>The only ſafe way of Sally, is that through the walkes, from whence the red Lyon in <hi>Graies-Inne-lane</hi> receives them with good quartering, and paſſes them through the back way in-the maine land: And ſo much for <hi>Skinke-Skonce.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="place">
                        <head>Milford Lane.</head>
                        <p>THe next is <hi>Milford lane,</hi> to which certaine Captaines and their companies being long ſince eaſhired, betooke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and liking the ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:15397:103"/>of it did there erect divers divers workes, both to the land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide and the water for their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaving.</p>
                        <p>As they came in by conqueſt, ſo they hold it by the ſword; and howſoever their title hath bin much diſputed heretofore, yet they have now commuted the matter, proud plantation, pretended the firſt diſcovery: and withal have reduced it, to a moſt abſolute Hance and free towne of it ſelfe without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency.</p>
                        <p>The chiefe benefit they have for ſecuring of their perſons is that of the water, for to the land there is little ſafety, when you are once without their works, &amp;
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:15397:103"/>therefore I will abide heere no longer, but hold my courſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the Savoy.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="place">
                        <head>The Savoy.</head>
                        <p>IF the <hi>Savoy</hi> ſhould not be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly defended every way and in every reſpect, it were a great ſhame to the diſcipline of the place, and the troups that are there billited, the rather for they conſiſt for the moſt part of Engyners and Projectors: and in memory of them have buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded there certaine tenements which ſhall beare the name of Projector-Ally for ever.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="place">
                        <head>Duke Humfrey.</head>
                        <p>FRom hence you muſt give me leave to paſſe by boat to <hi>Duke Humfries,</hi> which was a
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:15397:104"/>very ſtrong fortreſſe in former times, when the Megazine of munition, <hi>viz.</hi> the treaſury of To bacco-pipes was there eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</p>
                        <p>But the Megazine is removed, and the place much weakned, their Commanders diſperſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Budge-row, and ſcattered in Warwicke-lane, where they are the onely upholders of the three-penny ordinary (a ſtrange alteration)</p>
                        <p>The poore remainder of this Garriſon, unleſſe they be ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily relieved by them of the Colledge, to re-enforce the daily aſſaults of the enemy, muſt of neceſſity yeeld up all with much diſhonour.</p>
                        <pb n="189" facs="tcp:15397:104"/>
                        <p>I can ſtay no longer here with good name and fame, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I returne to my watermen attending all this while, who is to ſet me over to Southwark, and land mee at an excellent hold indeed, commonly called <hi>Montague-cloſe,</hi> ſometimes the Sene or the Monaſtery of Saint Saviours neere the bridge.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="place">
                        <head>Montague-cloſe.</head>
                        <p>AND though the Garriſion here conſiſt not of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny old Souldiers, yet their number is no whit inferiour to that of Ram-Ally, and ſome of them ſerve on bo h ſides, and are in both rolls ever attending where the ſervice moſt requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and the moſt of them are
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:15397:105"/>men of much activity.</p>
                        <p>The eldeſt company within it, are and have beene directly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in graine, deſcended from from the race of the old blew Brittaines.</p>
                        <p>In Lent when other Garriſons are moſt thinne and worſt victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alled, theſe doe moſt exceed in both, for then whole troops of Butchers from the Cantons ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning, offer themſelves like ſo many Switzers unto them: and convey by land and water to that place, ſuch aboundance of cattle fetcht firm the Kentiſh Kernes, and the Sorry Yonkry about them, as makes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves plumpe and paliable for any enterpriſe of all the yeere
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:15397:105"/>after, and alſo draws very great ſtore of Waſcoterians &amp; hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Basketerians unto them from all parts of the City and ſuburbs, &amp; al for meer carnality</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="place">
                        <head>Ely Rents,</head>
                        <p>THe laſt is that everlaſting liberty of <hi>Ely Rents</hi> in Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, which is ſo advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly mounted, that it com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mands all the levell beneath it. It is a worke of ſmall receipt for it may bee made good with—good, with three Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, two Coblers, a Baker, and a Tapſter, againſt all invaſions and invaders whatſoever.</p>
                        <p>I cite not that priveledge of <hi>S. Mertins le grand,</hi> with many other adjoyning, which have
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:15397:106"/>proper officers for returne of writs within themſelves; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe though they be not under command of the City, yet they admit no Sanctuary or refuge to the borrower, unto whom the fire and the frying-pan are both alike.</p>
                        <p>Theſe fore-mentioned Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, Forts, and Fortreſſes, ſtand ſtill in ſuch ſtate as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore expreſſed.</p>
                        <p>But I cannot forget the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate of others upon which the enemy hath entred, either by conqueſt or compoſition: Namely,</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="place">
                        <head>Cold Harbour.</head>
                        <p>THat of <hi>Cold Harbour,</hi> where was and excellent Blocke-houſe,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:15397:106"/>to correſpond with that of the cloſe on the other ſide. Both which together cleered the paſſage of the river between them, ſo that no water Bay liffe durſt come within their reachat point blanke.</p>
                        <p>And this (as they write) was taken in by the ſword in time of their ſecurity.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="place">
                        <head>The Fryers.</head>
                        <p>THe Fryers, Auguſtine and Cruciate, Blacke, White, and Gray great and leſſe, and thoſe of the Trinity. The Spitle and Saint Graces, had all their Cooles pul'd o're their heads, and ſo were all for the moſt part led into the City captive, where they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:15397:107"/>to this day.</p>
                        <p>'Tis ſaid that they were moſt loſt by this meanes, that they ſuffered thoſe of the freedome not only to dwell among them, but likewiſe to encreaſe &amp; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply, to plant and ſupplant, the Nobility and the Gentry which upheld their liberties; and in the end when they got and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſed all the power of office, truſt and authority, into their hands; they ſet open the gates and ſuffered the Military men of the Mace to enter and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe all.</p>
                        <p>The Commanders of the City were onely content upon treaty to article and agree with thoſe of the Blacke Friers;
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:15397:107"/>that notwithſtanding they ſo entred by conqueſt, yet the old companions, eſpecially the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Feather-makers, the Dutch Jewellers, the Scotch Tailers, and the French Shoomakers, with ſome forreigne forces, ſhould have and enjoy their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient priviledges, without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation or interruption of any kind.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="place">
                        <head>Great Saint Bartholmewes</head>
                        <p>BUt the greateſt blow that ever was given to the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower, was the taking of Great <hi>S. Bartholmewes,</hi> upon woſe plat-forme a whole Army of Borrowers and Booke-men might have beene muſtred and drawne out in length, or into
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:15397:108"/>what forme or figure it had pleaſed them to caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                        <p>What workes, yea what va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of art and workemanſhip was within it?</p>
                        <p>What an excellent halfe <hi>Moon</hi> was there caſt up without it for defence, towards <hi>Alderſgate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>What Sconces in the faſhion of tobacco-ſhops and tap-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in all parts of it. What art was in the Silke-weavers there, who in twiſting of their ſilke, made it ſerue like ſo many <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke</hi> lines to convey &amp; receive intelligence too and fro in an inſtant, &amp; laugh to ſcorn <hi>aſiniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum illum nuntium inanimatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="197" facs="tcp:15397:108"/>
                        <p>But alas, theſe are demoliſht, the old ſouldiers diſcharg'd, &amp; all delivered and yeelded up, upon compoſition and conſent of the Commander.</p>
                        <p>But the laſt packet we receive newes, that there are daily aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults made upon <hi>S. Iohn of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi> It is ſaid likewiſe that they are in a ſore Mutiny within themſelves; which if it bee ſo, the band of <hi>Borrowers</hi> there bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letted, will bee ſhortly diſ-ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and diſmiſſed utterly.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The Iubilees and dayes of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge follow.</head>
                     <p>THe unparaleld Parliament is the firſt, and of all others the beſt: the very <hi>tunc temporis</hi> wherein <hi>Iupiter</hi> hath the full ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:15397:109"/>of his influence, when he is in his Maſculine Houſe, and in a full aſpect <hi>(hor a optima.)</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The next is a time of a raging peſtilence: for if the Serjeants do not then feare the plague of God hanging over their heads, I know not what the Divel will feare them.</p>
                     <p>The next is the time wherein my Lord Maior takes his oath: For then the Serjeants and their Yeomen are all at Weſtminſter <hi>(hor a hona.)</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The next is that wherein the Sheriffes are ſworne: For in the fore-noone the Mace-men at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend their Maſters. At noone they have enough to do to wait upon M. Maior of <hi>Oxfords</hi> cups:
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:15397:109"/>&amp; in the afternoon, it is as much as they can doe to get home.</p>
                     <p>Other daies of priviledge are all ſuch wherein they are al ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally tyed for to attend their <hi>Sheriffes</hi> to <hi>Pauls,</hi> as that of <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> day, <hi>All-ſaints</hi> day, <hi>Candlemas</hi> day, the <hi>Coronation</hi> day, the <hi>Powder-plot,</hi> and the 5. of <hi>Auguſt, (hor ae mediocres,)</hi> On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take heede how you touch at any <hi>Taverne</hi> neere unto <hi>Pauls</hi> after the <hi>Sherifes</hi> are once ſet, &amp; untill they bee ready to depart, for feare of Free-booters.</p>
                     <p>I cannot ſay what hope there is in the priviledge of the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both,</hi> but there is great preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion uppon the benefit of thoſe times, wherein the <hi>Serieants</hi>
                        <pb n="200" facs="tcp:15397:110"/>we are their beſt apparell, for I have obſerved that they will make bold with their zeale, when they place much matter of conſcience in their cloathes.</p>
                     <p>The daies of their <hi>Spittle-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> are ſpeciall good ones: for their Maſters and Miſtreſſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then in Conjunction, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that they ſhould be dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diligent the while.</p>
                     <p>The dayes wherein the great Lords come down to ociate, or negotiate, cate, or treate with their Maſters, are very good.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whitſunday</hi> at the New-Church-yard does well, but I am affraid that they wil not be altogether ſo mad, as to be all compriſed within the peram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:15397:110"/>bulation of Bedlam, where I wil leave them at this time: &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede unto</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The markes of a conſcious cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Debtor, with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the Mace.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe be the markes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Uncertainty of meeting.</item>
                     <item>2 Obſcurity of walking.</item>
                     <item>3 Uariety of lodging.</item>
                     <item>4 Inconſtancy of abiding.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The particular marks follow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At the lanes end he ever lookes behinde him. And after hee is once turned out of ſight, hee mends his pace in an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary degree of Foot-man-ſhip, til he have gained ſome ground <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the followers. And then he
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:15397:111"/>makes another ſtand to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice whether any of them have arrived thither with more then ordinary ſpeed, or precipitate himſelfe at the comming about the lanes end, which is the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſigne of a Setter or a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant. He never keepes the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponticke paſſage. Hee hath a catalogue of of al <hi>Tavernes</hi> with backe doores, eſpecially to the waters ſide. Difference of attire (if hee have it) ſtands him in great ſtead. He envies the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Moone more then he pitties the decreaſe of his owne fortunes. Hee knowes there's little got by run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and leſſe by riſing at the Serjeants hands. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:15397:111"/>when he hath buſineſſe to doe on the next day, hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly removes himſelfe o're night, to the end hee may have a ſafe mornings flight. His mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings (when hee does ſay and hold) are in places where hee may ſtand as much upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation as his <hi>Taylor</hi> may upon his credit. With the Italian he does much miſlike the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſty maner of peace uſed by our nation in the City, (a place of civility, and that in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of their ordinary af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. Hee is better at retriving then at contriving. He is a great enemy to idleneſſe, for he loves not to ſee one leaning at a ſtall, or looking about him, where
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:15397:112"/>hee claimes no property, nor owes any ſervice, Hee learned of his Grandmother to hate whiſtling after candle-light a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things. He praies not in common forme, but that the Commons may meet in forme (as aforeſaid.) And no ſinne ſticks ſo impaſſively in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or diſperſes it ſelfe through is whole heart, as that he ever paid any thing to his Creditors in part.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The Diſcipline now offers it ſelfe, and the Mace is lifted up, in Terrorem populi</head>
                     <p>WIthin <hi>London</hi> there are two regiments of <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> The one is incamped in
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:15397:112"/>the Poultry: The other in Woodſtreet: The great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them attend their colours where they are ever ready to ſally upon the Alarum or ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall given. Other of them guard their Collonels perſon by turnes.</p>
                     <p>And the reſt are appoynted and expoſed (as followeth.) So many of the beſt able and moſt truſty in their Cavallerie, as their ſervice requires, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in terme time, are planted at Chancery-lane end, to make good that place, and to cut off ſuch as iſſue out of the works on the other ſide, or come downe from other parts to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the protection of them.</p>
                     <pb n="206" facs="tcp:15397:113"/>
                     <p>Of theſe Chancery-lane end men, if the deſigne doe deſerve it, ſome one or two are drawne out of them, to defeate the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage betweene the middle <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> and the <hi>Bell,</hi> or the <hi>Bar-gate,</hi> but this is upon eſpeciall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and therefore ſeldome at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, but when they have intelligence of ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary booty, or good pillage comming that way.</p>
                     <p>Others of them are quartered in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> where every mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, wedneſday &amp; friday, they ſtand charg'd with cocke up, ready to give fire at every poor Butcher in the graſiers quarrel, and theſe are of their Infantry.</p>
                     <p>Others are on every market
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:15397:113"/>day commanded for <hi>Leadenhal,</hi> where they ſerve one day under the <hi>Tanner,</hi> againſt the Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, another day under the <hi>Butcher</hi> againſt the <hi>Tanner,</hi> and ſometimes the <hi>Scrivener,</hi> againſt both. Others are appoynted to other ſeveral markets, where rather then they will want en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement, they will beare armes againſt the very butter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives (enough to make their hearts to melt with the very thought on't) the eldeſt ſort of them, ſuch as hold charge, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for their advice then their ability, are laid at the <hi>Exchange,</hi> where though the ſervice bee daily, and the Nation againſt whom they ſerve are all people of great ſtomack, meeting ever
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:15397:114"/>at dinner and ſupper times only, yet the danger is but ſmal in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard they have the Countrie round about to friend.</p>
                     <p>The onely Deſpervieos a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them are ſeverally ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to the ſeverall gates; where they ſcoure and keepe cleere the paſſage to the Barres, being the utmoſt extent of their workes. They are all right per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect at their Poſtures: As,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Beare your Musket under your left arme,</hi> id eſt, <hi>Be ſure to touch the priſoner on the ſword ſide. Pull out your ſcourer,</hi> id eſt, <hi>Draw your warrant. Advance your Pike,</hi> id eſt, <hi>Exalt your Mace. cocke your Match,</hi> id eſt, <hi>Enter your Action.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And ſo for every <hi>poſture,</hi> pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually and particularly in his order. Then for Strategems of war, they ride the ancient diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, quite dagger out of ſheath</p>
                     <pb n="209" facs="tcp:15397:114"/>
                     <p>The beſt that Roman Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries affoord us, is of that one noble reſolution, who to gaine beliefe and credit of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, mangled himſelfe, running out of the gates into their Campe to complain of his own miſery and his Countries ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, with offer of giving them up into the enemies hand, onely for actuation of his owne revenge.</p>
                     <p>But give me the plot that conquers at farre leſſe price.</p>
                     <p>A Porters Frocke (a Project of excellent carriage.)</p>
                     <p>A Lawyers gowne, <hi>(Latet quod non patet.)</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Scriveners Pen and Inke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne (a deſigne of deeper
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:15397:115"/>reach than you are aware on.)</p>
                     <p>Theſe ſhall make his paſſage, <hi>ſine ſanguine &amp; ſudore.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This is your onely Projector indeed, whoſe firſt anceſtor was begot between the <hi>man i'th Moone,</hi> and <hi>Tom Lancaſters</hi> Laundreſſe, upon a faire fagot pile, from whom are deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the onely Choriſters of our counter-quire.</p>
                     <p>It would doe you good to heare the whole packe of theſe together, they are ſo excellent for ſent and cry.</p>
                     <p>But the beſt mouth'd among them in truth, and for my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, the onely mouth is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Biſhopſgate.</p>
                     <p>And the beſt ſented at the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:15397:115"/>end of red-croſſe ſtreet, juſt at the entrance into Golding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane, into whoſe ſweet boſome I commit them all, and there leave them.</p>
                     <p>It may be expected that I ſhould ſay ſomewhat of the Diſcipline of the Bailiffes, but eſpecially of thoſe of the Vierge and the Clinkonians.</p>
                     <p>But ſome of them have no Diſcipline or order at all, and the reſt very little.</p>
                     <p>The poore Pichard cannot out pilfer them in the plaine path-way of their practiſe, they hold no good quartering with any man, but are more deſirous of prey then of lawfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
                     <pb n="212" facs="tcp:15397:116"/>
                     <p>The better ſort of them goe in bootes without ſpurres, and they for the moſt part are bought in Turning-ſtile lane in Holborne: the Author holds them not worthy his penne, or to be rank't with the men of the mace before mentioned, and therefore by his good will he will have nothing to doe with them at any hand.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Creditors part.</head>
                  <p>FOr the Debtors part, I am perſwaded that our Author hath performed it reaſonable well.</p>
                  <pb n="213" facs="tcp:15397:116"/>
                  <p>But for the other of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor (to ſay the truth) he hath practiſed that part very little hitherto, and therefore is very diffident of his ability therein.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Yet howſoere, hee'le ſtand upon his credit,</l>
                     <l>And iuſtifie his word, becauſe he ſed it.</l>
                  </q>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>For the charitable extent of the Creditors curteſie.</head>
                     <p>VErily this man of Credence doth obſerve theſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in all his proceeding of this nature.</p>
                     <pb n="214" facs="tcp:15397:117"/>
                     <p>Firſt, that he may lend or truſt upon ſuch conditions as may tend to the benefit of the Borrower or Debtor chiefly.</p>
                     <p>Then, that his owne gaine may be moderate.</p>
                     <p>Then, that there may be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord thereof kept for teſtimony of his ſincere intention, in two or three ſeverall bookes at the leaſt.</p>
                     <p>And laſtly, he doth not onely lend or truſt, but farther giveth it a bleſſing, that it may yeeld much increaſe to the borrower and debtor.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="215" facs="tcp:15397:117"/>
                     <head>The reaſons hereof are all as preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as pious.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 For it is better for him to build than to pull downe.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 He will not grinde the fore-head of his poore brother.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 His booke cannot erre, for it admits no tradition, but the pure and uncorrupted text it ſelfe, as it was delivered in the primitive regiſter, while <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> his fore-man was yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and did beare record as a faithfull witneſſe of theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
                     <p>And though the bleſſing be beſtowed upon a dead commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity,
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:15397:118"/>yet I hope it argues no ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition in him that giveth it.</p>
                     <p>And all this is apparantly good till we come to</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The myſtery of Multiplication.</head>
                     <p>TRadition, it is not tollerable but an abhomination, and yet our Creditor holds that Addition in the ſecret of ſhop-booke may be very well allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
                     <p>For ſo long as he doth onely make up in credits what he hath loſt in ſtocke, or what is decaid in neceſſary expences, and not riotouſly or vainly, ſeeing the wicked are but uſurpers of the
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:15397:118"/>riches of this world, it is lawful for him with an equall hand to be carried among his Debtors by way of apportionment, to rate and aſſeſſe them at his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</p>
                     <p>He will take no intereſt, nor wrong his conſcience for any good, his ſhop-booke hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto held good name and fame. Hereſies may creepe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church daily, but never into his ſhop-book in any wife: there is nothing there but what hath beene delivered, and his ſervants (eſpecially one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt) will as boldly as any Brewers deſperate Clarke maintaine and juſtifie it: ſhall he not maintaine his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:15397:119"/>myſtery, when they are both to be ſaved by the ſame faith? Why, he ſhall put the debtor in minde of the delivery of every parcell, with all the circumſtances to it, for he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members it as perfectly, as if it had beene done but yeſterday. Now the Debtor beginnes to quarrell the Shop-booke, my Creditor is moſt juſtly incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: And therefore now in the next place,</p>
                     <p>The Crow lookes to eat the Oyſter alive, but is caught in the attempt, and the hand in the Shop-booke breedes the winde-col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique in the warehouſe, which ſhak't the Fabrique
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:15397:119"/>and foundation of all his factory as followeth:</p>
                     <p>Suppoſe the tide is now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in, and the poore Oyſter gapes for ſome refection in the moiſture of it. The Birds of prey <hi>(ſcilicet)</hi> the ſhop-keeper the Crow, and the Vſurer the Cormorant: theſe hover about it, each of them hoping to pull it out of the little tenement where it dwels, and to devoure it alive. Hereupon the Cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and the Crow contend for the prize: The Crow claimes it as a Stray loſt, and left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the bounds of any watry coverture on the dry land at a low ebbe, The Cormorant challenges it nevertheleſſe, as
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:15397:120"/>being ſtill within his high wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-marke; Then the Crow al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges that it is ſo waſted (wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting water) that it is become no better than Carrion, and therefore it does properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto him. The Cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant denies that, and aſſures him that the Oyſter is yet alive, and therefore no carrion. But the Crow had given ſo much credit formerly, that he would now ſcarce beleeve his owne eyes (eſpecially in his wifes caſe) he would by no meanes beleeve this to be true, and therefore in hope to couſen the Cormorant, he deſires that he may onely feele with his bill whether it were ſo or no:
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:15397:120"/>Leave is given by the Cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, who thought it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the Crow to ſmell upon the prey, intending that never any more ſhould come to his ſhare: Then the Crow who knew how to ticle a Trout at his pleaſure, did without aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Conſtable or advice of Counſell, make a moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent entry upon the Oyſter, which preſently claps to his doore, ſhuts the Crow within, and caught him ſo faſt by his bill of entry, that all <hi>Colcheſter</hi> and the cuſtome-houſe can te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie to this day, with what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed and uncourteous en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement he was there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
                     <pb n="222" facs="tcp:15397:121"/>
                     <p>Well might the Crow cry and call for his companion the Cormorant to redeeme him from captivity, but all was in vaine. The doores were ſhut up, he could not ſo much as belch at the key-hole, or let out the winde which troubled the warehouſe by any meanes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or backward, the very foundation of the ſhop and ſhopbord were ſhaken with the violence thereof.</p>
                     <p>Being in this extremity, and ſo taken with the winde, that nothing applied inwardly could poſſibly helpe him, he cals for the ſhop-booke, and begins to conjure the collicke with ſuch terrible charmes and
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:15397:121"/>incantations, as the like were never deviſed nor put into any pentacle: Then he raiſed the great Prince, <hi>In primis,</hi> out of his Eaſterne Emperie, with a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of <hi>Items</hi> attending him.</p>
                     <p>Theſe two he ſets to taske, and enjoynes them to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh his Debtors in <hi>Spero,</hi> from thoſe in <hi>Deſpero,</hi> and to deale more plainly with him herein, than Widdowes uſe to doe by their Husbands eſtates in the Court of Orphans, and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: They performe his deſigne inſtantly, and the greater number appeared to be perdues directly deſperate and debilitate, amongſt the which my couſin Courtier and
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:15397:122"/>my Innes of Court-man were of the number.</p>
                     <p>The Courtiers ſuit did long languiſh and was palliated and upheld with letters commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, it complain'd much of the diſeaſe called the reference, it was a little lightened by a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall certificat laterly, yet in the end no meanes nor medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine could ſerve the turne, but of a ſtopping and obſtruction at the great ſeale it died.</p>
                     <p>The Innes of Court man was neither heire nor aged ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, for the enabling of any ſuch act as he had undertaken publikely by deed, or privately in the ſhop-booke. The Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the City counſaile, himſelf,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:15397:122"/>and all were fatally infatuated, betraid with a beard, and foold with formality.</p>
                     <p>The winde riſes more and more, the ſtorme increaſeth, ſtrange ſtitches on every ſide of the ſhop, wonderfull weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the ware-houſe, and convulſions in the Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord and boxe, complaine and cry out upon the Collicke, at whoſe mercy we leave him, expecting the eruption thereof very ſpeedily.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="226" facs="tcp:15397:123"/>
                  <head>The Signes fore-running the wonderfull Cracke.</head>
                  <p>THe certaine Signes in a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen are theſe:</p>
                  <p>He ſtrives to be call'd into ſuch office, eſpecially as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may have the ſtocke of the Pariſh or Company in his cuſtody.</p>
                  <p>He gives ground in matter of payment, the longer he deales, the more he leaves in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder upon every payment.</p>
                  <p>He leaves the plaine path of his profeſſion, and places more faith in a Project, then in all the probabilities of his owne Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding:
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:15397:123"/>and when a Citizen turns Projector, he has the very to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of the wonderfull Cracke upon him.</p>
                  <p>His Country houſe is too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for him, and it wants a gate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe for his Wife and Coach to come in at, and therefore there muſt be laid out in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thrice as much as the Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimple of all when it is finiſhed will affoord.</p>
                  <p>He takes up at intereſt to make good the building: all his good debts he ſets over to the immediate accountant in truſt, and with an intention to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent his Creditors.</p>
                  <p>All his purchaſes are either in the name of his ſonne, or
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:15397:124"/>ſome truſty Kinſman of his wives.</p>
                  <p>The neerer the Cracke, the faſter he laies about him, to take up in any kinde, and upon any conditions, then he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyes all things of value out of his houſe.</p>
                  <p>And at laſt he gives fire with a report of his great loſſes at or beyond the ſeas, where he (God wot) had never any facto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or dealing in all his life time.</p>
                  <p>Then he ſends his Wife to her Mothers, where ſhe muſt live a while, that ſhe may not be troubled with the noyſe and clamour of the Creditor.</p>
                  <p>He betakes himſelfe to his
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:15397:124"/>Chamber, keepes the ſhop win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes ſhut, and provides a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of all his deſperate cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits onely to deliver to his Creditors, when they ſhall come to treat upon the ſubject of ſatisfaction.</p>
                  <p>The newes reaches to the Exchange by noone, where they that have given credit to him, looke ſo prettily and pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully one upon another, as you might know and challenge them by their faces.</p>
                  <p>Then they gather together, and conferre their notes, and caſt up the whole ſumme what all their credits may come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, onely ſome of the more pragmaticall ſort, who feare to
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:15397:125"/>publiſh their loſſes leſt their owne eſtates ſhould come like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in queſtion, doe diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the matter, and ſpeake with the leaſt. Others that ſuſpect, it may be their owne caſe very ſhortly, pitty the mans misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, blame the hardneſſe of the times, deadneſſe of trade, and ſcarcity of coyne, recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what he is out for forraign plantations abroad, and other contributions at home, and with what charge he hath gone through ſo many offices in ſo ſhort time, whereat every man relents and lets ſlacke his more ſtrict purpoſes, agreeing all to goe to his houſe to confer with him after dinner.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="231" facs="tcp:15397:125"/>
                     <head>And ſo diſmiſſe we them till then.</head>
                     <p>IT may be you looke I ſhould have ſpoken ſomewhat of the Cracke of my City-gallant, but it is improper to place him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Creditors that has been bred a borrower from his Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and that according to the cuſtome of the Citie: let it one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffice, that though he had not his country houſe, yet he had his country Hoſteſſe, and though he dealt not in Court Projection, yet he kept a vile coile for court Protection.</p>
                     <pb n="232" facs="tcp:15397:126"/>
                     <p>His Hoſteſſe ſhe paid the old Widdowes and his young Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe their debts in the ſame coyne that he tendred to them.</p>
                     <p>And at laſt when his inſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency appeared upon every poſt, ſhe preferr'd any Iuſtice of peace his Clarke thereabouts to her reſpectuality before him, ſo that there was neither abiding at <hi>Rumford,</hi> nor returne to <hi>London,</hi> but he muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity make a voyage, be it but to Britleſey, where he lies cloſe under a borrowed name, which was the laſt commodity that ever he tooke up, till his friends ſhall have rectified his credit, and reſtored him to the
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:15397:126"/>eſtate from which he was ſo lately collapſed and fallen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The recovery of the old man, with the common comfort which it did beget, hold the next place.</head>
                     <p>AFter dinner all the Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors met againe on the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, where they hold full three houres conference, during which time not any one of them did beleeve one word which another ſpake unto him, for they were too wiſe and learned in the uſe and exerciſe of conformity, to ſpeake the ſimple truth, becauſe they were
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:15397:127"/>to deale in a matter mixt and compounded of many ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent credits commedled and put together.</p>
                     <p>From hence they goe to the houſe of their Debtor, in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as many as a whole col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Phyſicians to enquire for their Patient: they are forthwith brought up unto him into his Chamber, where they found him in an old ſuit onely fit for garbling or eating of green-fiſh, with as many night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caps upon his head, as there be cups in a neſt of Court diſhes, and the old gowne which was alwaies wont to lye at the Hall for ordinary dayes: in ſtead of plate there were onely two full
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:15397:127"/>Vrinals ſtanding upon the Court-cubbord, by which they might diſcerne the great diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and weakeneſſe, which the winde-collick had wrought within him.</p>
                     <p>And in ſtead of accounts, bonds and bils, and other evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, there lay onely open before him, the foreſaid Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue conſiſting of deſperate debts and debtors (as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid)</p>
                     <p>They ſalute him as if they did in a manner partly remember him, and then all together, as well the man of ten, as he of two and twenty hundred in credits, without difference, put forward for the firſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:15397:128"/>of his minde unto him.</p>
                     <p>This diſorder was much bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the graver ſort, and upon better advice, ſelect men were drawne out of them to compound, for ſo many as would voluntarily conforme themſelves, which was to be done according to the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, and as the ability would beare it.</p>
                     <p>In the meane time a letter of licence is ſealed for his liberty, to call in and recover what was due unto himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>This Letter of licence begat a commiſſion of conformity, and then to worke they goe full roundly: ſome of the chiefe who had taken other and better
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:15397:128"/>conditions of ſatisfaction of him in private, then the reſt, ſhewed much forwardneſſe in the publike way of compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in the end did ſo ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then their party, that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed againſt the other.</p>
                     <p>The whole debt was cryed downe to ſixe and eight pence in the pound, the windowes were opened, the ſervants in the ſhop flung up their caps, the Curſe was removed from their houſe, their Maſter was a reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered man, and none but a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querupt would ſay to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
                     <p>Their Miſtreſſe was ſent for home with all the ſpeed that might be, and this night all her
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:15397:129"/>kindred and their maſters friends were to ſolemnize this happy recovery of the decayed man, where they meant to drinke to the health of ſixe and eight pence, from ſixe in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening till eight next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="239" facs="tcp:15397:129"/>
                     <head>The common Comfort onely remaines.</head>
                     <p>NOw the recovered man makes a moſt ſtrickt ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teny and review into his ſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bookes, as well for debtors ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent as inſolvent; he confers his Regiſters all together, and where he findes a debt uncroſt in any one of them, though it be diſcharged in the other two it makes no matter, this is it by which he muſt ſtand charged, and unleſſe he can diſcharge himſelfe by this alſo, he is like to periſh and receive condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by the very letter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out tradition.</p>
                     <pb n="240" facs="tcp:15397:130"/>
                     <p>He will ſpare no man whom the Law puts into his hands, leſt he become a partaker in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity. He cals home all things which he had formerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed out of doores. And ſets forward his building in the country.</p>
                     <p>He flouriſhes as he never did before, and will give 1000. pound with his lame daughter now, more he then offered with her at the laſt ſwan-hopping.</p>
                     <p>Hee'le out-bid all the towne for the great and leſſer formes.</p>
                     <p>Briefly, he vowes:</p>
                     <p>To redeeme the time paſt.</p>
                     <p>To prevent the evill day to come.</p>
                     <p>To runne the courſe, and tread
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:15397:130"/>in the footſteps of ſome of the right worſhipfull, and in reverence of conformity to convert his old compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion gowne into a faire and comfortable foot-cloth.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>But three rich wives, and ſuch an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Cracke,</l>
                        <l>Will make thee ſcorne to cry <hi>(What doe you lacke?)</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="242" facs="tcp:15397:131"/>
                     <head>By the Counſaile of <hi>Ramme Ally.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <head type="sub">Non nobis nati ſumus.</head>
                     <p>VVHereas in theſe latter times it concernes us in civill pollicy, to be ſo much the more induſtrious as we are become numerous above for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages, and no endeavour can be ſo beneficiall and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable as the enlarging of our territory by diſcovery and plantation in parts habitable and agreeable with our debito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſpoſition, where we may diſperſe our Colonies with
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:15397:131"/>more conveniency and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage than at this preſent: for which purpoſe we have lately imployed and ſet forth the good ſhip, called <hi>(The leaſt in ſight)</hi> accompanied with that approved and well appointed Pinace <hi>(The pay nought)</hi> the charge and command of both which, we conferd upon Sir <hi>Oliver Owemuch,</hi> who man'd the ſame with perſons beſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified in the Art of Inſolvency, the greater part whereof, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had knowne and tryed to be men of much truſt, being his owne Creditors, and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of his owne diſcretion, whoſe loving kindeneſſes he required in manner of imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:15397:132"/>following, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His Mercer he made Maſter of <hi>(The leaſt in ſight)</hi> and his Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker Boat-ſwaine.</p>
                     <p>And becauſe his Vintner had beſtowed many a ſhot upon him in proſperity, he made him Maſter Gunner in his adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
                     <p>His Tobacco-man deſired to be the Gunners mate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would make all ſmoake againe.</p>
                     <p>A Purſer they needed not: for beſides that, they had all bad memories in calling of things paſt to remembrance, they held it a fooliſh thing to keepe accounts where there was no purpoſe of payment.</p>
                     <pb n="245" facs="tcp:15397:132"/>
                     <p>His Haberdaſher came ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what with the lateſt, but his Laundreſſe by the power of her Letters commendatory, preferd her husband to be Controller of the Coile, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer of the Bilbowes, and Yeoman Squabber of <hi>(The pay nought.)</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And his Taylor laſt of all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had the beſt ſtomacke to the action, he was made Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and had charge of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall for the voyage.</p>
                     <p>Being thus provided on Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the firſt of March, the winde blew faire from the Eaſt, when they left the Temple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaires; And the ſame day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saint <hi>Davids</hi> day, the ayre
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:15397:133"/>grew thicke and very foggy, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that the Pinace had loſt the Admirall, had it not in ſtead of a light in her Lanthorne, hung up a Leeke in the maine top, by the ſent whereof it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered ſight of her againe the next morning by breake of day.</p>
                     <p>On the ſecond, third, and fourth day, the weather was very variable and ſtormy, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they ſtill ſpoon'd on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for moſt advantage.</p>
                     <p>About eight of the clocke on friday the fifth of May, their Pylot who had beene a Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle-maker and a Proſpectuary without Temple barre, deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a ſaile making towards
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:15397:133"/>them, which they ſuſpected by his flag to be the water-bailiffe of <hi>London.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hereupon a Councell was call'd aboord, the Captaine to conſider what was to be done in this imminent extremity.</p>
                     <p>Some adviſed that it were fit to make to the land, if they knew where to touch without hazard.</p>
                     <p>Others of higher reſolution adviſed to ſtand the fortune of a Sea-fight, and to draw their number out of ſight into the hold, whereby to encourage the enemy to a neerer approch, which opinion was generally received and allowed.</p>
                     <p>Preſently, as the occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired,
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:15397:134"/>it was agreed that for the ſublimation of every ſparke Spirit amongſt them, there ſhould be an extraordinary al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance made inſtantly (that was) the full proportion of one pipe of Tobacco, and a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-pot of ſix to every two of them, which when they had cheerefully paſt about; the Taylor whoſe conſcience was more tender than his ſtomacke, would needs be reſolved in two points concerning his ſouls health before the fight ſhould begin. The firſt was, whether the cauſe and quarrell which they were to undertake were juſtifyable orno, for that he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver held Ludgate more worthy
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:15397:134"/>than Newgate in divers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects: and the next was in caſe he ſhould miſcarry in the action, whether <hi>Limbus patrum &amp; infantum,</hi> were not under his owne ſhop-boord or no.</p>
                     <p>Before my Taylor could have opinion herein of their Captaines Chaplaine, who had beene a Vineger-man former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and a fellow of excellent ſharpe apprehenſion: the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed enemy came within ſhot, whereupon every one of them began to apply him to his charge.</p>
                     <p>But juſt as Maſter Gunner was ready to let flye, (not for feare I hope) they perceived no other aſſailants but the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:15397:135"/>of new <hi>Brainford,</hi> who were bound for <hi>London</hi> to buy bels, not for the Church but their morrice dance againſt the enſuing Whitſon-ale. Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for their better recouery, the allowance was againe doubled to every one of them. And on they paſſe bravely till on Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the ſixth, they diſcerned firme land, lying upon the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyans Eaſtward. Here the Captaine drew out the one halfe of his forces, and with his long boat put them to land, where they found a moſt ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious continent fit for plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at foure degrees beyond the Temple, the climate excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding temperate ſo long as you
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:15397:135"/>pay the Tenniſ-court keeper for your lodging, the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modations moſt excellent, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thorow the white Hart in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Covent-Garden, and ſo into the Country round about; or from the great houſe thorow the Swanne into Drury-lane, and ſo forth free as bird in the ayre: The Lacedemonian wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſupply them with fiſh and fruit of all ſorts, which they bring downe in abundance from the upland countries: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as there is neither feare of want of victuals, ſo long as they haue money; Nor of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity while they doe put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the protection of Denmarke-houſe: Here they
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:15397:136"/>left the Haberdaſher and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine other to winter it, and the reſt returned aboord the ninth day of May, bearing their courſe ſtill Weſt &amp; by North: On the twelfth day, <hi>Cape Virde,</hi> or Greenes wharfe, did ſhew it ſelfe unto them, where they likewiſe put in, and forraged cleane thorow it on both ſides. This place (beſides other good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beaſts of all ſorts) is moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for Harts, whoſe hornes are of the comelieſt branch and ſpreading, as alſo of dimenſion and extenſion that can be; ſo that in memory of them, the Captaine named the place <hi>Harts-horne-Ally:</hi> Then the which no place hitherto diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered,
<pb n="533" facs="tcp:15397:136"/>is of a more capable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, or more rich in Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, Vegitatives or Victuals, or more agreeable with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of our countrymen, eſpecially if they be married. The ſeverall commodities and merchandizes whereof you ſhall receive more at large upon returne of the <hi>Leaſt in ſight,</hi> from thence.</p>
                     <p>In the meane time we exhort you that both with cheerefull contribution, and otherwiſe with your advice, you doe not onely uphold the old ones, but alſo further and advance the ſaid two new plantations ſo happily diſcovered, and ſo proſperouſly purſued hitherto,
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:15397:137"/>by you the Councell and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers of the ſaid company, and at your onely charge and expence.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>So ye that ſee't may wiſh, but never ſhall ye</l>
                        <l>Performe the like adventures as <hi>Ram-Ally.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15397:137"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
